<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way step by step to sound and saving conversion, with a clear discovery of the two states, viz: nature, &amp; grace: and how to know in which state one is, and the way to come out of the one into the other. Or, The ready and right path-way for the first Adams posterity to get out of their fallen estate accompanied with sin and misery, into the relation and family of the last Adam, which estate is attended with grace and glory, &amp;c. With many weighty questions answered, and cases of conscience resolved, for the clearing and confirming the truths asserted. / By Robert Purnell.</title>
            <author>Purnell, Robert, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1800_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 224:E1800[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way step by step to sound and saving conversion, with a clear discovery of the two states, viz: nature, &amp; grace: and how to know in which state one is, and the way to come out of the one into the other. Or, The ready and right path-way for the first Adams posterity to get out of their fallen estate accompanied with sin and misery, into the relation and family of the last Adam, which estate is attended with grace and glory, &amp;c. With many weighty questions answered, and cases of conscience resolved, for the clearing and confirming the truths asserted. / By Robert Purnell.</title>
                  <author>Purnell, Robert, d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Childe, and L. Parry, for Edw. Thomas at the Adam and Eve in Little Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170385:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WAY STEP by STEP To ſound and ſaving CONVERSION, With a clear diſcovery of the two ſtates, <hi>VIZ:</hi> Nature, &amp; Grace: AND How to know in which ſtate one is, and the way to come out of the one into the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> The ready and right path-way for the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity to get out of their fallen eſtate accompanied with ſin and miſery, into the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Family of the laſt <hi>Adam,</hi> which eſtate is attended with Grace and Glory, &amp;c. With many weighty queſtions anſwered, and caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience reſolved, for the clearing and confirming the truths aſſerted.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT PURNELL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 3. 3.</bibl> Except a man be born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matt. 18. 3.</bibl> Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdom of heaven.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke 13. 5.</bibl> Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. Childe,</hi> and <hi>L. Parry,</hi> for <hi>Edw. Thomas</hi> at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170385:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170385:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Impartial Reader.</head>
            <p>THough it be not expedient to be alwaies laying the Foundation, yet it is of abſolute neceſſity, that the Foundation be at firſt firmly laid: that ſo the building, notwithanding the Floods, Winde, and Storms, may ſtand, &amp;c. There are many waies to Damnation, and there is but one way to Salvation, &amp; that is ſtreight, and the Gate narrow; ſo that although the Runners are many, yet the Obtainers are but few: for except a man be born again, convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, regenerated, renewed and quickned, he cannot be ſaved; for we are by Nature Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath, and ſuch a one as this, even juſt ſuch a one, and no other, is a man, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man by Nature, ſuch a one was I, and you, and each of all the Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> that have been, or ſhall be, and that univerſally without any exception or reſervation, we are all gone out of the ways, we are all become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one: yet there is a way if we could light on it, how to poſſeſs what we want, and to live long in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, and to have one foot as it were in Heaven whilſt the other is upon the earth: to
<pb facs="tcp:170385:3"/>
point out that way was my endeavour in this Treatiſe. Reader, this ſmall peece is the birth of many Prayers, and a Deſcription of many choyce Experiences, and the ſum and ſubſtance of many ſolid and ſweet converſes, and the judgement of many precious Chriſtians; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would entreat the Reader, to weigh things in the Ballance of Righteouſneſs, and then I am almoſt confident, that there will be few or none that have the work of Grace upon their hearts, unleſſe they be under ſome violent fit of Temptation, or re-inſnared and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in a ſtate of Backſliding, but in the main will cordially own the enſuing Treatiſe; wherefore let the Reader rather amend what I have done amiſſe, than to carp, catch and bark at what he may ſuppoſe to be unſound, let him rather put pen to paper and correct the faults, and ſupply the defects, if he find any, that ſo this Book may be of great worth, though but of ſmall price. I am ſure this ſubject is the moſt ſeaſonableſt, and the moſt needfulleſt, that can be offered or preſented, Converſion being a moſt bleſſed work, and the day of Converſion the moſt bleſſed day that dawns, on this ſide Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf. It is true nothing is more common than for men to write of this ſubject, on the by, and by parts and pieces, but purpoſely on this ſubject, and alone, I know none, nor as yet could ever hear of any, beſides Mr. <hi>Whatleis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170385:3"/>
New Birth, &amp; Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Treatiſe of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo that a man may almoſt ſay, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more rare than to find Books, that are wrote purpoſely &amp; alone on this ſubject, &amp; thoſe few that are, are either ſo voluminous on the one hand, or ſcolaſtick on the other, that the Reader for want of Learning, and a better Memory, gains not altogether that benefit thereby, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he might. To draw towards a cloſe, Let me acquaint the Reader, that the beſt and chiefeſt Authors that I have conſulted withall, in the aſſerting and compiling the enſuing Diſcourſe, are the Prophets and Apoſtles men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, next unto them, not as infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible but as fallible men, knowing but in part. I have peruſed the writings of Mr. <hi>John Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebius,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sam: Boulton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Love,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Jenkin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Burroughs,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Norton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Francis Roberts,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thomas Brooks,</hi> and many others; but chiefly and principally. I have peruſed and made uſe of Mr. <hi>Whatleis</hi> New Birth, and Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Treatiſe of Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, finding my Spirit witneſſing the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ever ſaw their Books, for a great part; I have ſometimes named them, and ſometimes omitted it, and ſo do here recite it in general; I have not ſtep by ſtep followed the method of nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but here and there where I found things
<pb facs="tcp:170385:4"/>
fully proved by Scripture, and my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing me Witneſſe thereto, thoſe and ſuch like things I have taken, as helps in the compiling the enſuing piece, and no otherwiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reader, I doubt not through the Grace of God, and his bleſſing upon thee in the reading this Book, but Faith may be wrought in thee if thou haſt it not, or ſtrengthened if thou haſt it: and if ſo, I have my end, and thou wilt have the benefit. Let a mans ſin be never ſo great, if he believe, he ſhall be pardoned, if his Sin be never ſo ſmall, if he believe not, he ſhall be damned: the very ſin againſt the Holy-Ghoſt eſt is not unpardonable for want of Grace in our Saviour, but for want of Faith and Repentance in the ſinner, the cauſe of condemnation accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law is all ſin, but the cauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation under the Goſpel is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, and as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief contains in it all manner of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſo Believing containeth all Obedience; therefore this one Act of Faith is more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto God than all our Sins are unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Here thou art preſented with the means for the obtaining this grace of Faith, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces of the Spirit, and for the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Christ, to whoſe protection I leave thee, and ſubſcribe my ſelf thy Servant for his ſake,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT PURNELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170385:4"/>
            <head>A Table of the principal Heads in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and the conexion of theſe things together, and dependency of the one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Creation of Man. <hi>page</hi> 1</item>
               <item>Of the pleaſurable and delightfull condition he was placed in. 1, 2</item>
               <item>The manner of his fall, and the ſubtilty of Sathan therein. 4</item>
               <item>The ſad and miſerable eſtate he fell into. 5</item>
               <item>Man can never be ſaved, unleſſe born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. 8</item>
               <item>There be four Gates ſhut againſt him. 8, 9</item>
               <item>There be 18 ſorts of perſons that ſhall not enter into Heaven. 11, 12</item>
               <item>There be four reaſons why the Lord will not ſave them. 14</item>
               <item>Man is both unable and unwilling to help himſelf out of this miſerable eſtate. 20, 21</item>
               <item>There is a fourfold Change, and but one ſaving Change.
<list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170385:5"/>
                     <item>1. a Moral,</item>
                     <item>2. a Partial,</item>
                     <item>3. a Formal,</item>
                     <item>4. a Spiritual,</item>
                  </list>
Change. 16, to 26</item>
               <item>The preparations and qualifications that we are to find in our ſelves before we lay hold on Chriſt and the promiſes. 26, 27</item>
               <item>How Converſion, Regeneration, Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Repentance agree or differ. 28, 29</item>
               <item>Of the way ſtep by ſtep wherein the Lord doth lead a Soul out of a ſtate of Nature into a ſtate of Grace. 29
<list>
                     <item>1. The firſt ſtep to Converſion is Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. 29, 30</item>
                     <item>2. The ſecond ſtep is Vocation, which is accompanyed with
<list>
                           <item>1. The Faith of Aſſent.</item>
                           <item>2. Repentance.</item>
                           <item>3. Converſion.</item>
                           <item>4. Regeneration.</item>
                        </list>
35, 36, 37</item>
                     <item>3. The third ſtep to Converſion is to truſt or believe, which is accompanied with
<list>
                           <item>1. A looking unto him.</item>
                           <item>2. A comming unto him.</item>
                           <item>3. A receiving of him.</item>
                           <item>4. Laying hold on him.</item>
                        </list>
37, to 43</item>
                     <item>4. The next ſtep for the carrying on, and compleating this bleſſed work, there is dropped into the Soul, the Spirit of
<pb facs="tcp:170385:5"/>
prayer, which cauſeth the Soul chiefly to pray for theſe three things.
<list>
                           <item>1. For more Illumination.</item>
                           <item>2. For pardoning Mercy.</item>
                           <item>3. For purging Mercy.</item>
                        </list>
45, 46</item>
                     <item>5. The fifth and laſt ſtep that I ſhall name is this, the Lord doth cauſe the Soul ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to give it ſelf up, and ſurrender all the ſuppoſed intereſt that it had in its ſelf, to God that made him, and Chriſt that bought him. 49, 50</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Of Grace-begetting and Soul-converting Ordinances, which are,
<list>
                     <item>1. Hearing the word preached.</item>
                     <item>2. Reading the Scriptures.</item>
                     <item>3. Frequent and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>neſt prayer.</item>
                  </list>
51, to 54
<list>
                     <item>2 Dwell much upon Grace-breeding, and Soul-converting promiſes. 54 to 57</item>
                     <item>3. Frequent the company of Grace-beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and Soul-converting companions. 57, 58, 59</item>
                     <item>4. Call to mind and meditate upon Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begetting conſiderations. <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Conſider what Chriſt hath done for us.</item>
                           <item>2. Conſider how God hath dealt with other ſinners.</item>
                           <item>3. Conſider what relation thou haſt to him.</item>
                           <item>4. Conſider what engagements
<pb facs="tcp:170385:6"/>
you have from God.</item>
                        </list>
59, to 62
<list>
                           <item>5. Conſider in whoſe name you come before him. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. Means to gather and treaſure up a ſtock of Grace-begetting, and Soul-converting experiences. 62, 63, 64, 65</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Of the means to be uſed, that is more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially appointed for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſealing and aſſuring the Soul of Salvation. In the uſe of means take theſe four cautions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Be ſure they be means of Gods own appointment.</item>
                     <item>2. It is not the means alone, but Gods bleſſing upon the means, that doth help us.</item>
                     <item>3. His Bleſſing is not diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo much according to the means, as according to the uprightneſs of the heart, in the uſe of them.</item>
                     <item>4. Yet we are to wait upon God in the uſe of means, as it is Gods way of Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
65, to 73</item>
               <item>The want of Converſion is not in God, but in our ſelves 73, 74, 75<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 76.</item>
               <item>Some of the principal hinderances of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.
<list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170385:6"/>
                     <item>1. Ignorance of our own mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and Gods mercy.</item>
                     <item>2. Men think it to be either a needleſs, or an eaſie work.</item>
                     <item>3. A total neglect, or careleſs uſe of means.</item>
                     <item>4. Mens not conſidering the joyes of Heaven, and the torments of Hell.</item>
                     <item>5. Falſe conceits of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</item>
                     <item>6. Too deep a familiarity with bad company.</item>
                     <item>7. Ignorance of the grounds and princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ples of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</item>
                     <item>8. And laſt hinderance is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay.</item>
                  </list>
76, to 81</item>
               <item>Of the ſad condition of all that are not converted. 81</item>
               <item>Of the privileges and benefits of all that are converted. 82, 83
<list>
                     <item>1. They are Chiſts Servants.</item>
                     <item>2. They are his Friends.</item>
                     <item>3. His Brethren.</item>
                     <item>4. His Jewels.</item>
                     <item>5. His Sons and Daughters.</item>
                     <item>6. His Bride and Spouſe.</item>
                     <item>7. They are Co-heirs with Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170385:7"/>The tryals of Converſion, by which a man may know whether he be converted, yea, or no. 83, 84
<list>
                     <item>1. He that is converted doth deſire the word, and means of Grace.</item>
                     <item>2. He is willing to be made willing to do, whatſoever the Lord doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand him.</item>
                     <item>3. He is brought unto an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned hatred of the whole body of Sin.</item>
                     <item>4. His greateſt conflict is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in ward pollution.</item>
                     <item>5. He mourns for the ſins of of others, and the want of more grace in himſelf.</item>
                     <item>6. He doth delight to be ſpeaking of thoſe things w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> his heart hath taken in in the work of Converſion.</item>
                     <item>7. He doth begin to keep a watch over his own heart.</item>
                     <item>8. He makes Conſcience of keeping every known Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</item>
                     <item>9. He is willing to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the tryal.</item>
                     <item>10. He hath his Soul renewed in its faculties and vertues.</item>
                  </list>
85, 86</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170385:7"/>Cerrain Objections anſwered, which ſome out of weakneſſe, and others out of prejudice, may be apt to make againſt the foregoing Diſcourſe. 100</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Objections or Queries that are clearly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered are as followeeh.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> IF a people or a perſon refuſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Doctrine, and practiſe the Diſcipline of the true Religion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are not to be forced to receive the one, and practiſe the other, yea or no? 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether liberty of Conſcience be, as ſome ſay, a curſed tolleration, or of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution, yea or no? 101</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is or ought to be the ground of Communion and Fellowſhip in the Church of Chriſt? 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether there be any preparatory work required of men and women before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion? and iſ ſo, what it is? <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether there be not a free will remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> yea or no? 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether <hi>Adam</hi> by his fall did totally
<pb facs="tcp:170385:8"/>
loſe every good thing that there was in him, yea or no? <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How came the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> being but one, to become the ſin of ſo many, yea of all mankind? 104</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How could Chriſt being but one make ſatisfaction for the ſins of ſo many? <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are we to underſtand by election and reprobation, which ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about? 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether Election be the cauſe of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and Reprobation the cauſe of Damnation, yea or no? 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether Chriſt hath dyed and taſted death for every man, yea or no? <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How can they have hope to believe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whom God hath decreed ſhall not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? 107</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the moſt juſt and righteous God command all men to believe, and promiſe ſalvation to them that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and threaten damnation to all that doe not, ſeeing it is not in man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power to believe. 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Whether there be not a Light in every man, which if improved and walkt up to, would lead us to the Gate of Heaven, if not into Heaven, yea or no? 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doth it plainly appear, that our
<pb facs="tcp:170385:8"/>
Acceptation, and Salvation is only of Grace and nothing elſe? 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If Salvation be only of Grace without works, in what reſpect are good works neceſſary? 111, to 116</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall a man be able to do what is required, ſeeing he is not ſufficient of himſelf ſo much as to think a good thought? 116, 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is, or who is the Object of Faith? 120, 121</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What encouragements or grounds are there to provoke or perſwade a people to believe in God? 122, 124</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> In what way are we to concelve of God when we pray unto him? 124, 125</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How, or in what order are we to direct our prayers to the Trinity? 125, 126</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How can there be three, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, and yet but one God, ſeeing they are all called God? 126, 127, 128,</item>
            </list>
            <p>To each of theſe Queſtions there are clear and full Anſwers, which will ſatisfie all ſober, enquiring teachable people.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170385:9"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BY reaſon of the Authors abſence from the Preſſe, through the diſtance of his Habitation from the City, ſome faults have eſcaped the Preſſe; wherefore I pray thee do me the favour as to correct the greater faults that appear at firſt view, and paſs by in love the leſſer, and weigh theſe things in the Ballance of Righteouſneſs, Love, and Impartiality, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170385:9"/>
            <head>Of the Creation of Man, and the love of God to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde therein.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Great and Glorious God who is infinite in knowledge, wiſdom and love, having fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the glorious Frame of Heaven and Earth, according to his divine will, he calls a Council, even the operations in the Deitie, to build that excellent Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, Man: whom he made of the loweſt, and impureſt Element, Earth, and calls his Name Earth or Earthly, that the excellency of the work might appear ſo much the more glorious and wonderfull; the Lord having breathed into him the breath of life, he became a living ſoul, the man was now wholly good, juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; his Lord having ſuch a tender, intire and indeared affection towards him, would not put him into a vaſt world, but planted a garden of pleaſure and delight for him,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170385:10"/>
the flower of earths treaſure, it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with variety of fruites pleaſing to the eye, ſweet to the pallat, and decked with flowers and walks ſweet to ſmell to, pleaſant and delightful to walk in, and beautiful to behold, the pleaſant foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and filver ſtreames, gliding before him to water the garden, the ſweet drops of dew hanging upon the leaves and graſſe, like Jewels glittering, the tender branches and fruitful trees, continually clad in Summers livery, the Birds ringing out chiriping peals of melody, ſtraining forth their ſeveral notes, the nimble footed Beaſts leaping and ſporting in their fruitful pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, the Sun, Moon and Stars, as it were ſmiled upon him; here was no ſcorching heat, or freezing cold to diſtemper him, no ſickneſſe or pain to afflict him, no filthy or venomous thing to annoy him, no ſuch labour as to weary him, no contradiction or combuſtion to moleſt him, but a ſweet harmony and Concord amongſt all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet though all creatures were good, delightful and loving, man did ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them all, that there could not be found amongſt them any one fit or meet<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 2. 21, 22.</note> to be a companion for the man, that he might have ſociety with, <hi>So the Lord God
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170385:10"/>
cauſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deep ſleep to fall upon</hi> Adam, <hi>&amp; he ſlept, &amp; took one of his Ribs, and cloſed up the fleſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, and the Rib which the Lord God had taken from Man, made he a Woman:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o that no ſooner did the Man awake from his ſleep, but God preſented him with a lovely Companion, a Wife meet for him: the Man being now enriched with ſuch a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Ornament of Beautie, as to creatures compoſed of love, puritie, and innocencie. Now had the man one Jewel more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than all the reſt, one Flower more in his Garden, exceeding all others in beautie and delight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they might now diſcourſe of the goodneſs of God, and the excellenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Creation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leſt they ſhould in this Paradiſe of pleaſure and plentie grow too high in their own conceits, and ſo forget the Lord their God, he gave the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a righteous Law, that they might know they were but Creatures, and though they reigned as Lords and Kings on earth, yet they ought to be in ſubjection to their Creatour: ſo the Lord leaves him in the hand of his own counſel, under a ſtrict command <hi>not to eat of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil,</hi> with a Promiſe of Life up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on obedience to it, and threatening Death upon diſobedience of that righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170385:11"/>So <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> being in Paradiſe, and looking upon themſelves, as indeed they were, the moſt excellent Pieces of all the Creation, bearing the Image of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, This excellent eſtate did not long continue, for they both ſoon caſt off their Lords Precepts, by giving more credit to the words of the Serpent, than to the Word of their Creatour, and ſo fell by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, in the manner following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Devil being a fallen Angel, envying<note place="margin">The manner of <hi>Adams</hi> fall.</note> Gods glorie, and Mans happineſs, comes to the Garden, in the form of a Serpent, and firſt he boards the Woman thus, <hi>viz. Hath God ſaid, Ye ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at thereof?</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, it is a likely matter, that the Lord cares what you eat, what do you think, that he ſtands upon an Apple? hath he created all things for you? then do ye uſe them? this is the firſt Aſſault, which the Woman weakly reſiſteth, beginning at the firſt to yield: whereas God had ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt die, ſhe</hi> anſwereth doubtfully and ſaith, <hi>Leſt ye die;</hi> then the Devil percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ying the Woman to ſtagger, and the ground of her ſaith to ſhake, the word was no ſooner out of her mouth, <hi>Leſt ye die:</hi> but he replies, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely die;</hi> what, die, with eating ſo fair an Apple? can there be any hurt in it? O ſillie Woman, <hi>Ye ſhall not die</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170385:11"/>God he affirmeth, <hi>Ye ſhall die</hi> certainly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17.</p>
            <p>The Woman ſaith, <hi>Leſt ye die, Gen.</hi> 3. 3.</p>
            <p>The Devil that old Serpent ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall not die, Gen.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p>Well, who ſhall we believe? we ſee our Mother believed the Devil, for he had ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not die,</hi> but <hi>be as gods knowing good and evil, &amp;c.</hi> wherefore behold, O ſilly Woman, ſaith he, What a goodlie Tree is this, how pleaſant to the eie, delicate to the taſte, divine for uſe? Can it do you any hurt, would any but Fools abſtain, eat and fear not? then the Woman, ſeeing it was good for meat, pleaſant to the eies, and a Tree to be deſired after to get know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, ſhe took of it and did eat. And by theſe or the like Reaſons ſhe perſwaded her Husband, <hi>and gave him and he did eat,</hi> and hereby he brought himſelf and all his<note place="margin">The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery that <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; all his poſterity fell into.</note> poſteritie into an eſtate of death, ſin and miſerie. So thoſe who were created in the Image of God, and were told by the Devil, that by eating the Apple, they ſhould be as gods, by this one act of tranſgreſſion, he and all his poſteritie, (he being the Head and Root of all Mankinde,) were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the Image of Satan, being fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with pride, envie, anger and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, miſchief and crueltie; ſo that,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170385:12"/>1. The Devil is ſaid to be his <hi>Maſter, Rom.</hi> 6. 16.</item>
               <item>2. The Devil is ſaid to be his <hi>Father, John</hi> 8. 44.</item>
               <item>3. The Devil is ſaid to be his <hi>Prince, John</hi> 12. 31.</item>
               <item>4. The Devil is ſaid to be his <hi>God, 2 Cor.</hi> 4 4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And ſo man thus fallen bears the Image of Satan, which doth not conſiſt in any bodily ſhape, as ſome do fooliſhly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine; but in a likelineſs of all manner of wickedneſs, The <hi>understanding</hi> by this fall was darkened, and filled with vanitie, Pſal. 94. 11. and 2 Cor. 4. 4 The <hi>will</hi> depraved, the <hi>affections</hi> diſordered, the <hi>memory</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploied, the <hi>conſcience</hi> benummed. In a word, the wretched ſoul is ſo deſormed with filthineſs, outraged with paſſions, pined with envie, overcharged with glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, boiling with revenge, tranſported with rage, that the Image of God in Man is transformed into the uglie ſhape of the Devil, <hi>Gen. 6. 5. And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great, and that every imagination of the thoughts of his heart was onely evil, and that continually.</hi> And this fallen heart, not onely evil, but deſperately wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, <hi>Jer. 17. 9. The heart is deceitfull above all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170385:12"/>
things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> O Sirs, there are but few that doth know the plague of their own hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Man in this fallen eſtate, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a lump of ſinne, <hi>from the crown of the head to the ſoale of the foot there is no ſoundneſs.</hi> And ſo all the poſteritie of <hi>Adam</hi> have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glorie of God, and are now become Satans conqueſt, captives and ſlaves, being under the curſe, and ſubject to bondage and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Iſai 63. 6. So we are all as an unclean thing, and all <hi>our righteouſneſs as filtby rags,</hi> and we all do fade as a leaf, and our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties like the winde have taken us away. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Converſion,</hi> p. 71. affirms, that even our children, by nature, conſidered as finfull and unſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are as hatefull in the eies of God, as any Toads or Serpents are in ours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 10. Nay further conſider a little by what names and titles all men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, thus fallen, and ſo remaining, are<note place="margin">The names &amp; Titles given in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to fallen man.</note> known by in the Scriptures of truth, Sometimes they are called <hi>filtby dreamers, defiling the fleſh,</hi> Jud. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raging waves of the Sea foaming out their own ſhame,</hi> Jud. 13. <hi>Natural bruit beaſts, made to be taken and destroyed, that ſhall utterly periſh in their own corruptions,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 12. <hi>Wells
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170385:13"/>
without water, cloudes that are carried with a tempeſt, to whom the miſt of darkneſſe is reſerved for ever,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 17.</p>
            <p>A <hi>generation of vipers</hi> Mat. 3. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye ſerpents how can ye eſcape the damnation of hell,</hi> Mat. 23. 33. The Scripture calls them Lions for their fierceneſſe, and Bears for their cruelty, Dragons for their hiddiouſneſſe, dogs for their filthineſſe, and wolves and foxes for their ſubtilty, in a word, the Scripture ſtiles them Scorpions, vipers, thorns, briars, thiſtles, brambles, ſtubble, dirt, chaffe, duſt, droſſe, ſmoak, ſcum, and a <hi>cage of every unclean Bird,</hi> Rev. 18. 2. And if all this be not enough we are ſaid to be <hi>Satans ſlaves</hi> or <hi>captives,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 26.</p>
            <p>Man can never be ſaved, unleſſe he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated,<note place="margin">No ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> born again, and converted, and have the image of God renewed, which was defaced in our fall in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> Hence it is that Chriſt tells us, <hi>Mat. 7. 13. 4. Straight is the gate and narrow is the way that leadeth to life, and few there be that find it,</hi> There being four gates ſhut, and five ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions made by Chriſt againſt their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in; Firſt there are four gates ſhut.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Mat. 25. 12.</head>
               <item>1. The gate of hope,</item>
               <item>2. The gate of grace,</item>
               <item>3. The gate of mercy,</item>
               <item>4. The gate of comfort,</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170385:13"/>Secondly, there are five exceptions, made by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt againſt their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into heaven.</p>
            <p n="1">The firſt exception is that in <hi>John 3. 3. Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto him, verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, except a man be born again, be cannot ſee the Kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Exception is that <hi>Mat. 18. 3. Verily I ſay unto you, except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh,</hi> Luke 13. 3. 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you,</hi> John 6. 53.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Except your righteouſneſſe, ſhall exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſes, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the Kingdom of heaven,</hi> Mat. 5. 20.</p>
            <p>But moſt of the world will be apt to ſay,<note place="margin">Object.</note> we grant all this. <hi>But what is this to us? we have confeſſed our ſinnes, we have prayed, we have repented of our ſinnes, and in ſome good meaſure reformed our lives:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beware of temporary faith, partial obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> meſſionary love, pretended zeal, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal ſorrow, and feined humility, theſe may have the forme, and yet want the power of godlineſſe, except thy righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170385:14"/>
that of the Phariſees, thy ſacrifice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that of <hi>Cain</hi>'s, thy confeſſing of ſins, that of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s, thy weeping that of <hi>Sauls,</hi> thy faſting that of <hi>Abab</hi>'s, thy reformation that of <hi>Jehu</hi>'s, thy reſtitution that of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> thy believing that of <hi>Simon Magu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> thy fear and trembling that of <hi>Felix,</hi> theſe were caſt-awaies notwithſtanding theſe were ſeeming good things; Haſt thou never read of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> deſiring the prayer of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? Balaam</hi> deſiring to die the death of the righteous, <hi>Saul</hi> condemning of himſelf, <hi>Ahab</hi> humbling himſelf, <hi>Ninive</hi> repenting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Felix</hi> trembling, <hi>Herod</hi> hearing <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> joyfully, and did many things, <hi>Mark</hi> 6. 20. All this mayſt thou doe and more, thou mayſt live rejoycingly, and die peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and yet periſh eternally. Conſider if thou wert curſed in the wombe, born a child of wrath, what art thou now having lived ſo long in ſin, but the child of hell? farr more than thou waſt before, <hi>Pſal. 58. 3. Job</hi> 20. 11. Again, if for one fin all the curſes of the Law doe lie upon thee, as <hi>Gal. 3. 10. James</hi> 2. 10. what is due to thee for all thy ſins? If ſingle ſins deſerve death, what doe thy double and treble ſins deſerve? Conſider thy often backſliding, ſinnes againſt knowledge, conſcience, covenants, purpoſes, promiſes, proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170385:14"/>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not all theſe deſerve double and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per damation? <hi>viz.</hi> Not knowing of God he will not have mercie upon thee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 11. compared with 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 8. Not repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thou ſhalt periſh, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 3. Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in him thou ſhalt be damned, <hi>John</hi> 3. 18. Not loving him thou art curſed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22. Not being zealous according to knowledge, he will ſpew thee out of his mouth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 16. Not being meek, thou art abomination to the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 32. Not being mercifull, thou ſhalt have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without mercy, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 13. Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy, thou ſhalt never ſee the face of the Lord, Not waſhing thy heart from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thou canſt not be ſaved, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
            <p>Therefore ground this in the bottom of thy heart, That without true converſion, there is no hope of Salvation, <hi>Mat. 18. 3. John</hi> 3. 5 Sin was that which fetched the deareſt blood from the heart of Chriſt, and will have thine too, if thou getteſt not an intereſt in him: if thy ſin doth not die, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou doſt die, thou art in danger of<note place="margin">18 Sorts of men &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhall never enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> periſhing eternally. Read ſeriouſly but theſe four Scriptures, and thou ſhalt find at leaſt 18 ſorts of men and women that ſhall never enter into heaven, unleſs before they die, Chriſt be formed in them, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and renewed, born again and covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170385:15"/>1 Cor. 6. 9, 10.] <hi>Know you not that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God, be not deceived:</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. No Fornicators</item>
               <item>2. No Idolators</item>
               <item>3. Nor Adulterers</item>
               <item>4. Nor Effeminate</item>
               <item>5. Nor abuſers of themſelves with mankinde</item>
               <item>6. Nor Theeves</item>
               <item>7. Nor Covetous</item>
               <item>8. Nor Drunkards</item>
               <item>9. Nor Revilers, or envious perſons</item>
               <item>10. Nor Extortioners:</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God. <hi>Rev. 21. 8.] 11. Nor the fearfull and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>12. <hi>Nor murderers:</hi> See Rev. 22. 15.</item>
               <item>13. <hi>Nor ſorcerers, or thoſe that uſe witchcraft</hi>
               </item>
               <item>14. <hi>Nor Lyars, all theſe ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire, which is the ſecond death,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21.] 15. <hi>Nor he that is given to hatred, variance, and ſtrife,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>16. <hi>Nor he that is given to ſeditions &amp; hereſies,</hi> they which doe ſuch things ſhall not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the kingdom of God,</item>
               <item>2 <hi>Theſs. 1. 8.] 17. Nor ignorant perſons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>18. <hi>Nor thoſe that refuſe to practice what they know, being diſobedient.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe perſons being ſhut out of heaven,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170385:15"/>
makes good the words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 7. 13, 14. Enter ye in at the ſtrait gate, for wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which enter in thereat, becauſe ſtraight is the gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be which find it,</hi> Rom. 9. 27. <hi>Though the number of the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>he as the ſands of the Sea, a remnant ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, the holy nature of God will not permit the unclean and unholy ſoul to come into his preſence, Rev. 21. 27. <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe enter into it, any thing that de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, or whatſoever worketh abomination,</hi> Pſ. 5. 4. Neither ſhall evil dwell with him, the fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in his ſight, it is true you may call him Lord, Lord, till the laſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 21, 22. But he will tell you, he doth not know you, if thou haſt not ſomething of the image of that Spirit, that holy nature; whatſoever thou mayeſt think of thy ſelf, he will never take thee for his child, thou art wicked, <hi>and the wicked</hi> as <hi>Pſal. 9 17. ſhall be turned into hell, and all they that forget God:</hi> and ſurely God in the execution of the curſe, doth the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner no wrong; nay he ſhould doe wrong unto himſelf, and (with reverence ſo to ſpeak) be unjuſt, if he ſhould not execute Juſtice upon the ſinner, either in himſelf or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170385:16"/>
in his Surety: There are four ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To manifeſt the majeſtie of him who is offended,</item>
               <item>2. And the goodneſs of the command that is tranſgreſſed.</item>
               <item>3. The evil of ſin that is committed.</item>
               <item>4. The vildneſs of the ſinner for ſinning &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I had once thought to have ſpoken ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to each of theſe four heads, but ſhall not at preſent, but deſire the Reader to conſider, that every ſin puts God upon complaining, and Chriſt upon bleeding, and the Spirit upon grieving; Every ſin doth caſt a treble diſhonor upon God,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In its malignitie, as being moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the pure, unſpotted, and perfect na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In its obſtinacie, it oppoſeth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, ſlights the will of God, and contradicts the deſign of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Sin doth caſt a diſhonor upon God in its choice: a ſinner in ſinning, chuſeth a baſe luſt, a venomous ſin, a crooked way, before the glorious, precious, and moſt deſirable good, the Lord himſelf: So that man in the ſtate of nature, lives up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth as a condemned creature, under guilt, curſe and death, being conceived in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170385:16"/>
ſin, and brought forth into the world in iniquitie, having loſt that Image of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, holineſs, and ſaving knowledg of God, in which <hi>Adam</hi> our father was at firſt created, and ſo remains, till born again, converted and regenerated, the children of wrath by Nature, dead in ſins and treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Satans captives, ſervants, and ſlaves, and theſe men in this eſtate of Nature dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much one from another, one ſeems nearer unto, the other farther from the Kingdom of God, <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 34. compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 155. They</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have ſuch hardened hearts and ſeared conſciences that they commit all manner of wickedneſs with greedineſs, glorying in their ſhame, and ſo making themſelves (as the Scripture ſaith) <hi>ſevenfold more the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath than they were before, guilty of original ſin,</hi> but now they are become guiltie of original and actual tranſgreſſion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been filling up the meaſure of their iniquitie, and fitting themſelves for the day of ſlaughter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 32, 33. compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>James</hi> 5. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others walk more evenly and uſefully, being in a meaſure civilized by education, cuſtome, fear of puniſhment, good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wholeſome counſels: So was the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170385:17"/>
young man, <hi>Matth. 19. 20. All theſe things have I kept from my youth up: What lack I yet? &amp;c.</hi> So was the Scribe we reade of, <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 32, 33, 34 he anſwered diſcreetly, and Chriſt told him, he was not far from the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>Let the Reader conſider, that although Man is ſo fearfully and ſhamefully fallen, yet there r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mains ſome footſteps, marks and impreſſions of that righteous and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Law at firſt engraven in his heart by the finger of the Almightie, by which many Naturaliſts have acted wiſely and prudently as to worldly affairs and humane concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as may at large be ſafely gathered from many Scriptures: there may be a change and yet not The Change. Some of the Lord's people upon good ground doth obſerve that there is a ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fold change.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Change.</head>
               <item>1. A moral</item>
               <item>2. A partial</item>
               <item>3. A formal</item>
               <item>4. A ſpiritual</item>
            </list>
            <p>A man by improvement of the light and gifc in Nature, may obtain to the three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as to inſtance:</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a moral change, when a perſon or a people changeth from ſinfull notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous waies, to temperance, juſtice, equitie, patience, when ignorance is taken away by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170385:17"/>
illumination, and boldneſs in ſinning is abated by fear of puniſhment, and ſticks there, and goes no farther, and here thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſtay and live quietly, and periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a partial Change, when men forſake ſome ſins, and yet live in the love and liking of other ſins; Chriſt ſets this down in the Parable of the unclean Spirit, (as to ſome ſinfull courſes) is caſt out for a time, but afterwards returns with <hi>ſeven ſpirits, worſe than himſelf,</hi> and ſo his <hi>laſt end</hi> proves worſe than his <hi>beginning, Matth.</hi> 12. 43, 44, 45.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a formal Change, when men will do that which is commanded, but not as it is commanded, of theſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Tim. 3. 5. Having a form of godlineſs, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the power thereof,</hi> they will be doing of good, and forſaking evil, becauſe the eie of the creature, and the ear of the creature, the applauſe of the creature, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the creature, or the fear of the creature, prevails with them; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this threefold change, theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the former are in an eſtate of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangement to God, and liable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: for though the lives of ſome are leſs ſinfull than others, yet the hearts are alike, theſe men do but walk in new
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170385:18"/>
practices, with an old heart, <hi>Acts 7. 51. Heb.</hi> 6. 4.</p>
            <p>Conſider, O thou that readeſt, if thou and I had committed in all our lives but one ſin, and that onely in thought, this makes us ſubject unto, and leaves us in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of eternal damnation thereby, <hi>James 2. 10. Gal.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            <p>The Law muſt have a perfect, perſonal, univerſal, perpetual obedience, or elſe we remain under the curſe; according to the rule of moral righteouſueſs between God and Man, it followeth that the demerit of ſin receiveth its nature, meaſure and limits from the will of God, according as he hath revealed himſelf in the Moral Law. So that the damned in Hell ſuffer not more, nor leſs than they deſerved; yea, had God pleaſed to have inflicted a greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſin, yet had he been ſtill juſt: the object offended being God, the perſon ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering being but a Man, the evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot exceed the evil of the offence; neither can any thing relieve us, but that which is anſwerable to the evil of ſin: now there is no righteouſneſs in the world that is proportionable to the evil of ſin, but the righteouſneſs of Chriſt onely.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our own righteouſneſs is too ſhort, &amp; is called a monſtrous rag; a rag, and therfore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170385:18"/>
cannot cover us, monſtrous if it ſhould co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, it were but to cover filth with filth, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa. 30. 1. They cover but not with the covering of my Spirit, that they might add ſin to ſin,</hi> dung to dung.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor will the righteouſneſs of the Law be large enough, if a man could keep it, it will not acquit us for former diſobedience, <hi>Gal. 3. 21. If the Law could have given life, verily righteouſneſs ſhould have been by the Law.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3, 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not the righteouſneſs of all the Angels that can do it, becauſe this alſo is a created righteouſneſs, a finite righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and no way proportionable to the evil of ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we ſhould weep as many tears as the Sea holds drops, and humble our ſelves as manie daies as the world hath ſtood mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, all this were too ſhort to purchaſe the pardon of one ſin; if the ſtung <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> had made a Medicine of the beſt Herbs in the Wilderneſs, and a Plaiſter of all the ſovereign Ingredients in the whole World, and applied it with Mountains of Praiers, Seas of Tears, this would not have helped them, if withall they did not look upon the Brazen Serpent; for all theſe cannot purchaſe the pardon of one ſin, nothing but infinicen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs can deal with ſin, it muſt be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170385:19"/>
infinite Wiſdom to finde out a Way, it muſt be infinite Mercy to pardon, infinite Power to ſubdue, infinite Merit to purge and cleanſe, and infinite Grace to deſtroy ſin. Look about thee, whoſoever thou art, that readeſt theſe Lines, this is or was thine eſtate and condition, which is attended with theſe two Miſcries, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Thou art unable to help thy ſelf out.</item>
               <item>2. Thou art unwilling.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt of the firſt:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thou art unable to help thy ſelf out, <hi>Jer. 13. 23. Can the</hi> Ethiopian <hi>change his skin, and the Leopard his ſpot, then may they do good that are accustomed to do evil?</hi> There is no power below the power that raiſed Chriſt from the dead, that can turn the heart of a ſinner to the Lord, he is as well able to turn a Flint into Fleſh, as to turn his own heart to the Lord, he is as well able to raiſe the dead, and to make a World, as to repent, for Repentance is a Flower that grows not in Natures Garden; as the Birth of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not by the ſtrength of Nature, like <hi>Iſhmael's</hi> of <hi>Hagar,</hi> but by virtue of the Promiſe, after a ſupernatural manner, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſenſibleneſs of barrenneſs, ſo ſeemeth it to be with everie one that is born of the Spirit. <hi>John</hi>ſaith, that <hi>Believers were born
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170385:19"/>
not of the will of the Fleſh, nor of the will of Man, but of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou art as unwilling as unable, thou haſt wilfully pulled upon thy ſelf juſt miſerie, and art apt wilfully to reject free mercie: there is a ſpecial enmitie in the heart againſt Converſion and Believing, <hi>John 5. 43. I am come in my Fathers Name, and ye receive me not, if another ſhould come in his own name, him ye would receive. Acts 22. 4. I</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> before converſion) <hi>perſecuted this way unto the death. Rom.</hi> 10. 3. They would <hi>not ſubmit to the righteouſneſs of faith:</hi> Here are proud hearts indeed! that it ſhould be matter of ſubmiſſion, for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned man to take a Pardon, a wounded man a Plaiſter, a ſick man a Cordial, a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man Cloathing, a loſt ſinner a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; ls not this the caſe of the Men and Women of the World? Conſider, wouldſt thou not account him a Fool, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Phyſick becauſe he is ſick, a Cordial becauſe he is faint, Meat becauſe he is hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, Money becauſe he is poor, Cloathing becauſe he is naked, and Freedom becauſe he is Satans Priſoner? I could almoſt ſay to the Reader, as once <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Thou art the Man, 2 Sam.</hi> 12. 7. There are amongſt manie others theſe four things that keep moſt Men and Women from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing converted,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170385:20"/>1. Moſt think it to be a needleſs work, or an eaſie work, when as it is a needfull work, and a hard work, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 23. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 3.</item>
               <item>2. Or becauſe he is not able to pay that which God requires.</item>
               <item>3. Or becauſe he thinketh he ſhall be able to diſcharge all himſelf in time.</item>
               <item>4. Or elſe becauſe he doubts of the truth of him that promiſeth to help him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So much ſhall ſerve to ſpeak of the</p>
            <list>
               <head>Change.</head>
               <item>1. Moral</item>
               <item>2. Partial</item>
               <item>3. Formal</item>
            </list>
            <p>It remains now that we come to the fourth, to wit, the Spiritual change: and here I ſhall fix, all that is written before is but an Introduction to this, I have been ſhewing the Maladie, let us now come to the Remedie, the ſum whereof is; that God the Father, Son, and Holie Ghoſt hath ſent forth Jeſus Chriſt, God-Man into the World, to ſeek and ſave ſinners, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth every one that heareth theſe glad tidings <hi>to believe in him whom he hath ſent;</hi> and promiſeth that <hi>whoſoever believeth in him ſhall be ſaved, for God when the fulneſs of time</hi> (by him appointed was come) <hi>ſent his Son,</hi> him that is God over all, bleſſed for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver, equal with the Father in being, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170385:20"/>
and glorie, him in whom his Father<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>R. F.</hi> in his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. pag. 7.</note> delighted from all eternitie, his own and his onelie begotten Son, promiſed before to <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3. 15. preached to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12. 3. typified in the legal Sacrifices, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 18. and propheſied of by <hi>Moſes</hi> and all the Prophets, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 18. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 4. and pointed at by <hi>John,</hi> the Lord ſends his Son in the likneſſe of ſinfull ſleſh, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ſin in the fleſh, him we are to hear, and to wait upon in a broken-hearted and diligent uſe of meanes, untill we be made partakers of his free ſaving grace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And although in this great work, I ſhall, I fear, rather liſp, than ſpeak plain, yet I truſt I ſhall not darken counſel by words without knowledge. It is true, ſometimes a child of light doth walk in darkneſſe, as to the footſteps of the Lord: <hi>Pſal. 77. 19. Thy way is in the Sea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy footſteps are not known;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this with <hi>John 3. 8. The wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but canſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t tell whence it cometh, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it goeth; ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit,</hi> ſaith our Lord Chriſt, &amp;c. From theſe and other Scriptures it doth appear, that God doth not work in the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and method upon all in the work of converſion; ſome are ſanctified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170385:21"/>
womb, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. 5. as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was ſanctified before he came out of his mothers womb, and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was filled with the Holy Ghoſt even from his mothers womb, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 15. Some are converted by a <hi>ſmall ſtill voice:</hi> See 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 11. 12. ſome muſt have a <hi>great and strong wind,</hi> renting the mountaines of ſinne in their hearts, others muſt have an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> to awaken them, ſome muſt be brought through the fire to burn up their droſſe, ſome men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fleſh is harder to heal then others, ſo ſome mens hearts; a needle may do that to one, which a launce will not do to another; a frown to one, which a blow will not do to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſome men are of greater parts, of greater places, who are not ſo eaſily hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; ſome men are of crabbed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towards ſpirits, and knotty blocks had need of hard wedges: ſome men have long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſcores, and greater rekonings, have been greater ſinners than others, and though not alwayes, yet ordinarily God doth proportion the ſorrow to the ſinne. Again, upon ſome the Lord doth intend to beſtow a greater meaſure of grace, than upon others, and ſo he layeth a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable foundation; ſome he intends to uſe as one of a thouſand. To comfort others therefore he doth exerciſe them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170385:21"/>
with difficulties of higher nature, that they may experimentally comfort others, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 4. and ſome he intends for great ſervice, great imployment, either in Church or State, and therefore he doth humble them the more at the bringing in, as we may ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and read, in the converſion of <hi>Paul, Luther, Auguſtin;</hi> It is true, all Gods people are ſouldiers; but all his people are not Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions: all are brought home, or ſhall be; but all are not brought home equally alike in every thing; and though the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a ſinner be a great work, yet when the Lord ſets about it, it is ſoon done;<note place="margin">Though converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be a great work, yet it is ſoon done.</note> Vocation, regeneration and converſion, is many times wrought in an inſtant; God in ſaying, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, ariſe from the dead and Chriſt ſhall give thee life,</hi> makes the ſoul to awake, ariſe and live, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the twinkling of an eye, <hi>Iſa. 45. 22. Look unto me and be ye ſaved, all the ends of the earth, for I am God, and there is none elſe.</hi> Chriſt tells us in few words, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in as few, <hi>John 3. 14. As</hi> Moſes <hi>lifted up the Serpent in the wilderneſſe, ſo muſt the Sonne of man be lifted up, that whoſoever believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him ſhould be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 10. 9. <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart, that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170385:22"/>
But to proceed, conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What preparations, conditions, or qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſhould a man or woman find in themſelves, before they lay hold on Chriſt and the promiſes?</item>
               <item>2. How Converſion, regeneration, repentance and vocation, agree or differ?</item>
               <item>3. The way ſtep by ſtep, which the Lord in his ordinary diſpenſation, in theſe Goſpel dayes, doth lead a ſoul, as it were by the hand, out of a ſtate of nature, into a ſtate of grace, &amp;c?</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. <hi>What preparations, conditions or qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould a manor woman find in themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they lay hold on Christ, and apply the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?</hi> For anſwer hereunto, take theſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, <hi>Viz.</hi> I know no qualifications &amp; preparations that are ſo required, as that without it we ſhould not come, but there be ſome, without which we will not come, we muſt <hi>buy milk and wine,</hi> although it be <hi>without money and without price,</hi> Iſa. 55. 1, 2. By preparatory work, we underſtand certain inherent qualifications, according to the ordinary diſpenſation of God: and ſo the ſoul is made ſenſible of ſinne, death, and curſe due to it; before it paſſe through the new birth, he muſt be convinced, that the Law is holy, juſt and good, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept holy, the promiſe good, the curſe juſt; a man muſt acknowledge himſelf a lawfull captive, before the Lord will ſet him free;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170385:22"/>
all the preparations required in Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way of diſpenſation before conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, may be reduced to theſe four heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt dying for the ſinnes of the people, according to the Goſpel of free grace, and ſo tenders pardon of ſinne to all ſinners that are ſenſible of ſinne, <hi>ſinners that are broken hearted,</hi> Iſa. 61. 1. <hi>broken and bruiſed,</hi> Luk. 4. 18. <hi>that are weary and heavy laden,</hi> Mat. 11. 28. poor <hi>ſick ſinners,</hi> Mar. 2. 17. ſenſible of their miſery, and neceſſity of a remedy, without which they periſh eternally.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After this ſenſe of miſery and want of mercy, there will be an inquiring after a remedy, <hi>Sirs, what ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> Rom. 16. 30. So <hi>Paul, Lord, what wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou have me to do?</hi> Rom. 9. 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There will be a waiting upon God in the uſe of means, for the obtaining of mercy.</p>
            <p>But let the Reader conſider, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever preparations and qualifications there is required in any before converſion, they are wrought in us by the ſinger of God, who <hi>worketh in us both to will and to do of his own good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2. 13. <hi>So then it is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſheweth mercy,</hi> Rom. 9. 16. how was <hi>Paul</hi> diſpoſed, and affected
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170385:23"/>
when Chriſt calls him? <hi>Acts</hi> 9. had not <hi>Pauls</hi> calling depended upon Gods choice at that time, he had never been called; here may we behold the downfall of all natural preparations, and meritorious diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Quere 2. <hi>How Vocation, converſion, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, regeneration, agree or differ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer to this, let me give the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Maſter <hi>Baxſters</hi> judgement, to which I fully aſſent and conſent; All theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular expreſſions, ſaith he, are uſed in Scripture to expreſſe one and the ſame work upon the ſoul, onely they have ſome ſmall difference, <hi>Viz.</hi> The word Vocation, is taken for Gods act of Calling, and is two-fold. Firſt, Common; when men are brought to an outward profeſſion. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Specially; when people are ſavingly converted to Chriſt; this laſt calling is the ſame with converſion, only this difference; Calling hath uſually in Scripture a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal reſpect to the firſt act on the ſoul, even the act of faith it ſelf, or at leaſt the habit of faith, is effected in the heart, and therewith the ſeed of all graces in the ſoul; this is that Vocation, or ſpecial effectual Calling: next, Conſider that Repentance is the ſame thing as ſpecial effectual Calling, only this difference, the word Vocation,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170385:23"/>
doth principally expreſſe the ſtate to which we are called; but the word Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, doth principally reſpect our our turning to God, from whom we fell, and the word Vocation doth as much or more reſpect our coming to Chriſt, the true and only way to the Father; the word Regeneration is more comprehenſive, than Converſion, Repentance and Vocation: becauſe there is ſo great a change, that a man is as it were another man, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 11. He that is in Chriſt is a new creature.</hi> And yet the word Regeneration fignifieth the ſame thing as Converſion, Repentance and Vocation, only obſerving a ſmall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, as before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Quere 3. <hi>The way ſtep by ſtep, which the Lord in his ordinary diſpenſation, in theſe Goſpel-dayes, doth lead a ſoul, as it were by the band, out of a ſtate of nature, into a ſtate of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt ſtep to Converſion, is Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſtep to accompliſh, or at leaſt to carry on this work, is effectual Vocation, which hath many branches.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third ſtep to get out of a ſtate of nature, into a ſtate of grace, out of a ſtate of death, into a ſtate of life, is to truſt or believe in the Lord, which hath many branches.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170385:24"/>4. The fourth ſtep; for the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and carrying on this work, there is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually dropped into the ſoul and heart the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication, by which the party goes unto God, with confeſſions and petitions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth ſtep; to effect and compleat this great work, the Lord doth cauſe the ſoul ſecretly to give it ſelfe up, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the intereſt that it had in it ſelf, to God that made it, and Chriſt that bought it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt ſtep to Converſion, is illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, as doth fully appear by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Acts. 26. 18. I ſend thee,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Paul, to open their eyes, and to turn them from darknes to light, and from the power of Sathan unto God.</hi> So <hi>Pſal. 119. 130. The entrance of thy word giveth light, it giveth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding unto the ſimple,</hi> lob. 33. 30. <hi>to bring back his ſoul from the pit, to be enlightned with the light of the living,</hi> Men are not born with this ſaving light in their hearts, as they are born with tongues in their mouthes; for the beſt knowing men under heaven, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till born again and converted, are in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Epheſ. 5. 8. <hi>For ye were ſometimes dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but now are ye light in the Lord, being born again,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 14. <hi>The natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, neither can
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170385:24"/>
he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 6. <hi>For God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This illumination is acompanied with (1) A re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the mind, <hi>Rom. 12. 2. Eph.</hi> 4. 23. (2) A conviction of ſin and guilt, he doth acknowledge himſelf a lawfull captive. (3) There are the ſeeds, or roots of all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, infuſed into the ſoul at once, if the ſoul be enlightned with a ſpecial ſaving light, but the ſoul doth not preſently, &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly exerciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all; the firſt part of ſaving grace is illumination, the opening of the eyes, cauſeth the opening of the heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſtep to accompliſh or at leaſt to carry on this work of converſion, is Vocation; this effectual vocation, is the firſt or ſecond act of Election, ſaith Maſter <hi>Norton;</hi> Calling is the firſt act of Divine mercy, in recovering miſerable man: Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Twiſs</hi> ſaith, effectuall calling is the firſt mercy, &amp;c. But let the Reader conſider, that if theſe four words, Vocation, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Repentance, Regeneration, agree in one, and are uſed in Scripture to expreſſe the ſame work upon the ſoul, having but a ſmall difference, as hath been proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; then now in ſpeaking to this word
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170385:25"/>
Vocation, let the Reader take notice, that though Converſion, Repentance, Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, be not expreſt, yet they all are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and contained; and if ſo, then Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſeems to be a ſecond work upon the ſoul, rather than the firſt, <hi>Jer. 31. 19. Surely after that I was turned, I repented, and after that I was inſtructed I was aſhamed, yea, even confounded, becauſe I did bear the reproach of my youth;</hi> the way that the Lord doth take for the recovering of a backſlider, and the converſion of a ſinner, doth in many thing; if not in all, go hand in hand together, he calls upon the one, and ſo he doth upon the other, he enlightens the one to ſee from whence he is fallen, and ſo he doth the other; he gives repentance to the one, and ſo he doth to the other, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>There are principally theſe three things, to be conſidered in this Vocation,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The principal cauſe of Vocation is Gods free mercy, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 9. Titus</hi> 3. 3, 4, 5.</item>
               <item>2. The inſtrumental cauſe is the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 14.</item>
               <item>3. The end of Vocation is Gods glory, and the ſalvation of his elected ones, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>And you hath he quickened, when you were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes,</hi> Col. 2. 13. <hi>And you that were dead in your ſinnes, hath he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170385:25"/>
Eph. 1. 12. <hi>that we ſhould be to the praiſe of his glory.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There be certain ſteps at firſt in a ſouls coming to Chriſt, or preparatory acceſſes, like that we read Pſalm 6. 2, 4. <hi>Have mercy upon me, O Lord, for I am weak; O Lord heal me, for my bones are vexed; Return, O Lord, deliver my ſoul: O ſave me for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake.</hi> Matt. 9. 20. <hi>Bebold a woman diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> though ſhe came not preſently to look God fully in the face, though ſhe dare not come to touch Chriſt and lay hold on him, yet ſhe was ſenſible of her own miſery, and want of mercy, ſhe knew there was vertue to come from him, and ſhe came as near that as ſhe durſt, ſhe had a deſire to ſpeak, but ſhe went no farther than to ſpeak to her ſelf; ſhe ſaith to her ſelf, <hi>if I may but touch his garment, I ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>whole;</hi> then Chriſt ſpake to her, though ſhe would not ſpeak to him, to overcome her baſhfullneſs, he called her <hi>daughter,</hi> and to overcome her unbelief, he bid her <hi>be of good comfort, he had healed her.</hi> From how little a ſpark, how greata fire! from how little a beginning, how great a proceeding! ſhe deſired but the hemm of his garment, and had himſelf. See <hi>John. 3. 2. Nicodemus</hi> he <hi>came to Jeſus by night,</hi> who was ſo weak, as being either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid or aſhamed to own Chriſt in the day,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170385:26"/>
he cometh to him by night; One would have thought, that Chriſt would have ſaid to him, <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> is thy deſire after me ſo ſaint, as that thou feareſt to come to me in the day time? Or am l ſo unworthy as not to be owned, but out of fight? Haſt thou either ſo low an eſteem of me, or beareſt thou ſo little love to me? Goe return as thou cameſt, I will not accept of thee in the dark, who wouldeſt not acknowledg me in the light. No, no, Chriſt hath not one ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of this, he knew that <hi>Nicodemus</hi> was but a beginner, and therefore entertaines him, and inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ructs him in the new birth, John. 3. 5. <hi>Except a man be born of water and of the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God &amp;c.</hi> Conſider there is none effect of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, before illumination and effectual vocation; the el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t themſelves are ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>to be children of wrath</hi> as well as others. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. 3.</p>
            <p>Some affirme, that in this act of Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſeeds or root of faith, is wrought in the heart, which may be true, onely, (under correction) I doe verily think it is not exerciſed, but in part; the Soul doth exerciſe but little more, than to give credit to what is written, which ſome call the faith of credence, giving credit, to what is written, which others call the Faith of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170385:26"/>
aſſent; this undoubtedly is wrought in the heart, either in the work of Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or in eſtectual Vocation: now effectual Vocation, or ſpecial effectual Calling, is attended or accompanied with, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Faith of aſſent.</item>
               <item>2. Repentance.</item>
               <item>3. Converſion.</item>
               <item>4. Regeneration.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now moſt of theſe words are uſed in Scripture, to expreſſe the ſame work upon the ſoul, as Mr <hi>Baxſter</hi> affirmes, or rather as the Scripture teacheth us, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſpecial effectual Calling is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or accompanied with the Faith of aſſent, or credence, See <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 2. The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per did aſſent to the power of Chriſt, that he was able to clenſe him, ſaying, <hi>Lord if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean;</hi> ſurely Vocation is accompanied with a bare naked aſſent to every truth revealed by God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is accompanied with Repentance, which conteineth two things. The firſt is, a hearty ſorrow that ever he ſinned. The ſecond is, a turning from that ſinne to God, or there is a turning from a ſtate of ſinne and miſery, unto God our only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; this Repentance is wrought, by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170385:27"/>
the Miniſtry both of Law and Goſpel; the thunders of the Law terrifie, and the dews of the Goſpel mollifie: there is nothing breaks the heart more than mercy, nothing melts a man more than the mercies of God, which he hath abuſed; the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this, opens all the ſprings in thee, the ſoul is not able to ſtand ſtubborn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſpecial effectual Calling, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with Converſion, which is a work of the Spirit of Chriſt in a ſenſible loſt undone ſinner, by the Doctrine of Chriſt, by which he effectually changeth the minde, heart and life, from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to God in Chriſt; the parts of this Converſion are theſe three:- Firſt, it is a change of the minde: Secondly, of the heart: Thirdly, of the life, &amp;c. In the moment of Converſion, God works that bleſſed work, which ſhall never be undone; In a word, that is wrought in an inſtant, which ſhall remain for ever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This effectual Calling is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Regeneration, which doth make ſo great a change, that a man is as it were an other man, ſo that this word Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is more comprehenſive, than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, Repentance, or Vocation, 2 Cor. 5. 17. He that is in Chriſt, is a <hi>new creature,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170385:27"/>
old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new;</hi> Mark, every man that is in Chriſt, that is, thus converted, every true Chriſtian then is a new creature, not in ſubſtance but in quality, all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new; a true converted man, he hath new love, new deſires, new ſorrow, new delight, new reſolution, and a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, Vocation, Converſion, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, is wrought in an inſtant, God in ſaying live, makes the ſoul to live; as it is in the firſt, ſo it ſhall be in the ſecond Reſurrection, <hi>in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye,</hi> whiles God ſpeaks the word, the dead ſhall riſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 52, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3. The next ſtep to get out of a ſtate of death, into a ſtate of life, is to truſt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Lord. I know there be many that doth make this the firſt ſtep to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I hear them ſay, but not prove; ſure I am, no man can have grace without knowledge; for who can hate ſinne till he knoweth it, and the evil of it? and who can love God or believe in him, till he know him to be merciful, able and faithfull? who can do the duty that he underſtandeth not, or go the way to heaven that he is ignorant of? ſo that illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt needs be the firſt ſtep, but withall it is granted, that the Spirit of God, either
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170385:28"/>
in Illumination or Vocation, doth cauſe the firſt act of faith in the heart, and by that act a habit is effected, and therewith the ſeed of all graces; For the habit of faith, ſaith Maſter <hi>Norton,</hi> ſeemeth not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed alone, before the other habits of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace. The univerſal frame of ſaving grace is infuſed into the ſoul at once, as one general habit; ſo that the infuſion of life, into the heart or ſoul, hath its being all at once, and is uncapable of diviſion into parts; and ſo the habit of faith ſeemeth not to be infuſed alone, before or after the other ſaving graces, ſo that I am not ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what comes into the ſoul firſt, but what the ſoul doth put forth and act firſt, in order to its coming out of a ſtate of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into a ſtate of grace.</p>
            <p>Two things are here of an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to our ſalvation; the one is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve unfainedly that Chriſt is the Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the world, and that there is no other way of ſalvation, but by him, <hi>Acts 4. 12. Iohn 14. 6. Iohn 10. 1, 7, 8, 9.</hi> The ſecond is, to accept of him as he is offered to us in the Goſpel, and ſo faith inſtates a ſoul in the poſſeſſion of heaven, whilſt the body remains on the earth; Now in this third ſtep, of truſting in God or believing in him, the ſoul and heart doth in ſome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170385:28"/>
meaſure, exerciſe theſe four things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It doth look unto him.</item>
               <item>2. It doth come unto him.</item>
               <item>3. It doth receive him.</item>
               <item>4. It doth believe in him, and lay hold on him.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It doth look unto him, <hi>Iſa. 45. 22. Look unto me, and be ye ſaved all the ends of the earth, for I am God, and there is none elſe,</hi> Zach. 12. 10. <hi>And they ſhall look upon me whom they have peirced, and mourn for him, as one mourneth for his only ſonne;</hi> The ſoul looks upon an humbled Chriſt, with an humble heart, upon a broken Chriſt, with a broken heart, upon a bleeding Chriſt, with a bleeding heart, upon a wounded Chriſt, with a wounded heart; in a word, this is ſuch a look, as ſends a man away with another heart, <hi>Pſal. 34. 5. They look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him and were lightened;</hi> there is no change of the ſubſtance of the ſoul and body, nor of the faculties of the ſoul and body, but the qualities of the faculties are clearly changed, ſo that men and women become as children in humility, teachable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and beginning the world a new; he hath a new heart, and a new tongue, new inclinations, new intentions, new deſires, new content, and diſcontent, new delight, new anger, new courage, new fear, new
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170385:29"/>
hope, new thoughts in his heart, and new work to do, and yet, as before, there is no change of the ſubſtance of ſoul and body, nor of the faculties of the ſoul, but the qualities of the faculties are clearly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſoul doth not only look unto him, but it doth come unto him, <hi>Mat. 11. 28. Come unto me all ye that are weary, and heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,,</hi> John 6. 37. <hi>Him that cometh to me. I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> Some affirm, that in the Greek, this word hath three negatives, thus, <hi>I will in no wiſe, no wiſe, no wiſe cast out,</hi> and if ſo, Let the Reader conſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord doth call thee three times in one verſe, Iſa. 55. 1. <hi>come, come, come;</hi> So in Rev. 22. 17. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride ſay, come, and let him that heareth come, and let him that is athirſt come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As there are three calls, Come, come, come; ſo there are three ſorts of perſons invited to come, and all couched in the latter words of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of <hi>Rev. 22. And whoſoever will, let him take of the water of life freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What perſon ſoever he be, <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentil, Barbarian</hi> or <hi>Scythian,</hi> Acts 10. 34. 35. <hi>Then Peter opened his mouth, and ſaid, of a truth, I perceive, that God is no reſpecter of perſons, but
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170385:29"/>
in every nation he that feareth him, and worketh righteouſneſſe, is accepted of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What finner ſoever he be; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth not the weeping <hi>Mary,</hi> the begging <hi>Canaanite,</hi> the intreating <hi>Publican,</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing <hi>Thief,</hi> the adultero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Woman,</hi> the denying <hi>Diſciple,</hi> the perſecuting <hi>Paul,</hi> Iſa. 1. 18. <hi>though your ſinnes be as ſcarlet they ſhall be cleanſed &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What time ſoever a ſinner doth come; ſo it be before the ſun is ſet, the glaſſe out, and the golden ſcepter taken in, if it be at the eleventh houre, or as the Thief upon the Croſs, at the laſt gaſp, it may be thou mayſt obtain mercy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, he doth aſſure thoſe that come, he will in no wiſe, in no wiſe, in no wiſe, caſt of: Now lay all theſe together, the Lord calls, Come, come, come; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that he calls are of three ſorts, (1) what perſon ſoever, (2) what ſinner ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, (3) what time ſoever he come; if he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed come to me, I will in no wiſe, in no wiſe, in no wiſe, caſt off.</p>
            <p>3. So there is not only a looking upon him, and a coming to him; but there is a receiving of him, <hi>John. 1. 12. but as many as received him, to them gave he power, to become the ſons of God;</hi> by the habit of faith the ſoul doth paſſively receive Chriſt, but by the act
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170385:30"/>
of faith, the ſoul doth actively receive Chriſt. In the firſt, the ſoule is paſſive; but in the ſecond, he is active; there is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold receiving of Chriſt, a paſſive and an active; paſſive, wherein the ſpirituall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of grace is ingenerated, or infuſed into the heart or ſoul, and ſo we are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of Chriſt, before we do receive Chriſt; ſo that Chriſt in working the grace of faith receiveth us, and by the act of faith we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him; ſo that Chriſt taketh the ſoul, before the ſoul taketh him.</p>
            <p>Now he that hath thus received the Son hath life. 1 <hi>John. 5. 12. he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life.</hi> Collo. 2. 6. <hi>As ye have therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt the Lord, ſo walk ye in him.</hi> He that truely receiveth Chriſt, receiveth him in all his offices, as a King, Prieſt and Prophet, this receiving of him, is not an act of the underſtanding, but an act of the will, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing him, and truſting on him.</p>
            <p>4. The heart doth believe in him, and the ſoul layes hold on him, ſo that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned place, <hi>John</hi> 1. 12. they and they only becomes the Sons of God, that doth believe in his name; when the Jaylor <hi>Acts.</hi> 16, 30. would know <hi>what he muſt do to be ſaved?</hi> the apoſtles anſwered him and ſaid, Vers. 31. <hi>believe on the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170385:30"/>
Christ, and thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> ſo when the people asked Chriſt, <hi>what they ſhould do that they might work the works of God,</hi> John. 6. 28. <hi>Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto them,</hi> Vers. 29. <hi>this is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent.</hi> So 1 John. 3. 23. This is his commandment, <hi>that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the name of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 12. <hi>I know,</hi> ſaith the apoſtle, <hi>whom I have believed;</hi> there is the firſt act of faith of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, and <hi>I am perſwaded, that he is able to keep, that which I have commited to his truſt;</hi> there is the ſecond act of truſt.</p>
            <p>When the ſoul is brought over to aſſent unto that great truth, that Chriſt is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and a Mediator, it doth rowl and reſt it ſelf upon him, and ſo truſteth on Chriſt for juſtification, and conſequently for ſalvation, <hi>Pſal. 37. 5. Commit thy way to the Lord, truſt alſo in him,</hi> Prov. 16. 3. <hi>Rowl thy works upon the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</hi> Caſt thy burthen upon the Lord, Pſal. 28. 7. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, and my ſhield, my heart truſteth in him.</hi> The Lord is the Author and Finiſher of our faith, he doth command us to believe, he doth enable us to believe, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends us for believing: ſo the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> for his faith, which was only the faith of his own powerful work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170385:31"/>
ſo he commends <hi>David</hi> for his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> for his perfectneſs, <hi>Moſes</hi> for his meekneſs, <hi>Cornelius</hi> for his devotion, the <hi>Publican</hi> for his compuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the poor <hi>Widdow</hi> for her liberality, and the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> for her faith and importunity; all which was only the work of his own grace in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O how may this encourage us to ſtir up our ſelves, and take h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld of God! See <hi>Iſa. 64. 7. Iſa. 27. 5. Let him take hold of my ſtrength, and he ſhall make peace within me.</hi> As there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to us, till we believe; ſo if once we believe, all the promiſes are ours; he hath promiſed to be a tower, a rock, a refuge, a covert from a ſtorm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>, and hidden place in time of danger; he hath promiſed to hear us when we pray, to anſwer us when we call, to open to us when we knock, <hi>Pſal. 50. 15. Mat.</hi> 7. 7. Ground this in the bottom of your hearts, that without faith in Chriſt, and obedience to Chriſt, there is no promiſe of life and ſalvation, by Chriſt, no coming to the Father but by him, no coming to Chriſt but by faith, no getting of faith but by waiting upon him in the uſe of means, &amp;c. And ſo to cloſe up the fourth head, let the Reader conſider, that this looking unto him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto him, receiving of him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170385:31"/>
in him, is ſpiritually to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly to be performed.</p>
            <p>4. Step; for the carring on, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating this work, there is dropped into him, or her, the Spirit of grace, by which he is at length imboldened to go unto God, with confeſſions, and petitions, he puts on the reſolution of the King of <hi>Ninive,</hi> Jonah 3. and ſaith within himſelf, <hi>I will cry mightily unto the Lord, who can tell, but that he may have mercy upon me?</hi> He prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for theſe and the like things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He prayes for more light, that he may ſee his ſinnes, and the vildneſs of them more fully, that he may arraign, accuſe, and judge himſelf for them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He prayes for pardoning mercy; <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don my ſin,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>for it is wondrous great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He prayes for purging mercy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He prayes for an increaſe of light, that he may ſee his ſinnes more fully and clearly, that he may abhor, arraign, accuſe and judge himſelf for them, <hi>That which I ſee not, teach thou me,</hi> ſaith the Prophet. Again, Job. 13. 23, <hi>How many are mine iniquities and my ſins? make me to know my tranſgreſſion and my ſin.</hi> Job 40. 4. <hi>Behold I am vile, what ſhall I anſwer thee? once have I ſpoken, yea twice, but I will proceed no farther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170385:32"/>2. He prayes for pardoning mercy: Rom. 8. 15. <hi>We have received the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abba Father;</hi> As a little child at firſt ſaith <hi>Dad</hi> and <hi>Mam:</hi> ſo doth a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; the evidence that the Lord gave <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi>'s converſion, was this, Acts 9. 11. <hi>Behold he prayes!</hi> He that hath not this breath of Prayer, is either a dead man, or in a dangerous ſwoun, Pſal. 25. 7. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the ſins of my youth, nor my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, but according to thy mercy remember me for thy goodneſs ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He prayes for purging mercy, Pſal. 19. 12. <hi>Who can underſtand his errors? cleanſe thou me from ſecret faults.</hi> Pſal. 79. 9. <hi>Purge away our ſins for thy name ſake:</hi> the ſoul is not ſatisfied with pardoning mercy, unleſs he may have purging mercy alſo; ſo that pardoning mercy is ſo great a belly-mercy, that it hath many mercies in the bowels of it; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19. it brings <hi>reconciliation</hi> with God, and admiſſion into his favour, and adoption of children, whereby the ſoul hath acceſs to God as a Father, with child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like boldneſs, and acceptation of our ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſanctification of every condition to us, and ſupportations under tryals and croſſes; and laſt of all, peace, joy, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which are not ſo much fruits of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as fruits of purging, and keeping down
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170385:32"/>
of ſin, that it reign not in our mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. He freed me from the guilt of fin, and ſhall I love the filth of fin? He made me a member of Chriſt, and ſhall I be a filthy member of ſo holy a body? He hath made me a branch, and ſhall I be a polluted branch of ſo holy a ſtock? the Lord forbid.</p>
            <p>Let the Reader conſider, that although we have brought Prayer under the fourth Step, or head, yet this is to be underſtood, that the habit or root of this grace or gift, was infuſed or conveyed into the heart and ſoul in the firſt ſtep, to wit, illumination: but it lay there, as fire under aſhes, or ſap in the root of the tree, it was ſtill and dumb, it did not open the mouth, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the heart, until Vocation and Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had made way; If wee did conſider what order and method the Lord doth take to unveil his love to man, and what order and method man ſhould take to apprehend and apply this love, it will make much for our ſatisfaction: <hi>Viz.</hi> Gods order is, he goes downward, from the Cauſe to the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and we muſt goe upward, from the Effect to the Cauſe; he goes from Election downward, we muſt go from Illumination, Vocation, Regeneration and Believing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: and thus God and we at laſt ſhall meet in the middle way: we muſt prove our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170385:33"/>
ſelves to be called, and he will acknowledg us to be elected. Let us conſider that golden chain, <hi>Rom. 8. 29, 30. For whom he did foreknow, he alſo did predeſtinate; moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and whom he called them he alſo justified, and whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified, &amp;c.</hi> Here is a golden chain indeed, no link thereof can be unlinked, becauſe the faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, is from and by the Lord, Firſt whom he fore-knew for his own, as the word is taken, <hi>John.</hi> 10. 14. 27. thoſe whom he marked out, as it were, out of all other men in the world, and ſet his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon, (2ly.) he alſo did predeſtinate, that is, ordained, to be conformable to Chriſt their head in part, both in grace and glory, (3ly.) Moreover whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo called to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of faith, by the outward preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, and the inward and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual operation of the ſpirit, and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified; that is, God merely of his own grace and free will forgiveth our ſinnes, and pronounceth us juſt: juſtice and mercy doth both meet in this juſtification; juſtice, in that he will not juſtifie a ſinner without a perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and mercy, in that he will accept of ſuch a righteouſneſs, that is neither in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170385:33"/>
us, nor done by us, but by our ſurety for us; all eminent acts, as juſtification, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, ſanctification, are but one act in God, as we have proved before; but becauſe of our darkneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teachableneſs, the Lord doth ſpeak to us after the manner of men, and ſo doth make out things gradually to us, leading us from ſtep to ſtep, from things more plain, to things more and more hard, as we are able to hear, and underſtand and practice them.</p>
            <p>5. The fifth and laſt ſtep that I ſhall name, for the carrying on, and compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this work, is, the Lord doth cauſe the ſoul ſecretly to give it ſelf up in an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, and ſo to ſurrender all the intereſt that it had in it ſelf, to God that made it, and Chriſt that bought it; and ſo his ſoul is carried forth to a ſecret reſting, relying, leaning, ſtaying, and hanging upon the mercy of God, in Chriſt alone, for life and happineſſe: Now he looks after, and endeavours to be found in walking in the way of ſanctification, he reads and finds, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 2. that if he be elected to life, it <hi>is through Sanctification of the Spirit unto obedience,</hi> and 2 <hi>Theſ. 2. 13. God hath choſen a people from the beginning to ſalvation, through Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170385:34"/>
of the Spirit, and belief of the truth:</hi> He labours for holineſs as well as happineſs, he reads and findeth that the word of God hath a purifying faculty in it, <hi>John 15. 3. Ye are clean through the word that I have ſpoken to you,</hi> Pſ. 119. 9. <hi>Wherewith ſhall a young man cleanſe his way, but by taking heed thereto, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy word,</hi> Pſ. 119. 11. <hi>Thy word-have I bid in mine heart, that I might not ſinne against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Grace-begetting and Soul-converting means for all heedfully to attend upon, that hope to enter into Heaven.</head>
               <p>THere are ſprings of Grace, or pipes of conveyance, which if cut off, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, we may live in ſinne, and die in ſinne, and at laſt go to hell; but if we heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and frequently make uſe of them, we may live in the fear of the Lord, and die in his favour, and enter into heaven; theſe means are for the increaſing holineſs, as well as for the attaining it, and therefore we are not to ſatisfie our ſelves with making uſe of them now and then, but frequently and willingly; for the ſame meanes that doth work the work of Illumination, doth alſo work the work of Converſion, Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170385:34"/>
Regeneration, Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp;c. And not only work and beget theſe in us, but increaſe it, and cauſe it to flouriſh, and grow up from one degree of grace to another, untill we come to the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Sonne of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt; the means follow.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Keep cloſe to Grace-begetting and Soul-converting Ordinances.</item>
                  <item>2. Dwell much upon the meditation of Grace-begetting Promiſes.</item>
                  <item>3. Frequent the company of Grace-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting and Soul-converting companions.</item>
                  <item>4. Be frequent in the cheriſhing of Grace-begetting Conſiderations.</item>
                  <item>5. Gather and treaſure up Grace-beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and Soul-converting Experiences.</item>
               </list>
               <p>1. Keep cloſe to Grace-begetting and Soul-converting Ordinances, and they are theſe three,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The hearing of the word preached.</item>
                  <item>2. Reading of the Scriptures.</item>
                  <item>3. Frequent and earneſt Prayer; Firſt, of the Firſt,</item>
               </list>
               <p>1. Hearing of the Word preached, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37, 41. it was by hearing <hi>Peter</hi> preach, that the Jews were <hi>pricked at the heart, and converted, and three thouſand added to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170385:35"/>
Church at once,</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 17, 18. God ſent <hi>Paul</hi> to preach, for the <hi>opening of mens eyes, and turning them from darkneſs to light,</hi> by teaching ſinners the way of God; <hi>David</hi> aſſured himſelf they ſhall be converted to him, Pſal. 51. 13. <hi>the word of god is the ſeed of life,</hi> which is ſown and takes root in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hearts of them that God will ſave, 1 Pet. 1. 23, 25. <hi>It is the word of God which is the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible ſeed, by which we are born again;</hi> it was thoſe that <hi>had ears and heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not,</hi> that were not converted and born again. <hi>Mark.</hi> 4. 12. &amp;c. as we ſhould hear the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in order to converſion, ſo for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of faith in our hearts, Luke. 10. 17. <hi>Faith cometh by hearing,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 13. <hi>in whom alſo ye truſted after ye heard the word of truth the Goſpel of our ſalvation,</hi> Iſai. 55. 3. <hi>hear and your ſoules ſhall live.</hi> Now in the uſe of this bleſſed meanes, obſerve theſe four rules, and thou ſhalt never miſcarry, but get ſomething by every Sermon thou heareſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Try the doctrines preached, by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Act. 17. 11. <hi>they received the word with all readineſs of mind, and ſearched the Scriptures daily whether thoſe things were ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Receive what thou findeſt agreeable to the word, as from the Lord, 1 Theſſ. 2. 13. <hi>for this cauſe alſo thank we God, without ceaſing, becauſe when ye received the word of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170385:35"/>
God, which ye heard of us, ye received it, not as the word of man, but as it is in truth the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Keep in memory as much of it as may be, <hi>James 1. 25. Being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer, Heb. 2. 1, 2. Therefore we ought to give the more earneſt beed to the things which we have heard, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t at any time we ſhould let them ſlip:</hi> verſ. 3. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſalvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Indeavour to practiſe it thy ſelf, and communicate it to others, <hi>Mat. 7. 26. Every one that heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them not, is like unto a fooliſh man that built his houſe upon the ſand.</hi> James 1. 25. <hi>But whoſo looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed;</hi> therefore be ye doers of the Word, and not hearers only, deceiving your own ſouls.</p>
               <p>2. The next Faith-begetting, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converting Ordinance, is, reading the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, many a ſoul hath had happy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the benefit of reading the Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. for <hi>the Law of the Lord is perfect, converting the ſoul,</hi> Acts 8. 28. The Eunuch was reading in <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and in the 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, we read he was converted and baptiſed. 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 13. Till I come give atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170385:36"/>
to reading,</hi> Rev. 1. 3. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of this Propheſie,</hi> Acts 17. 11, 12. <hi>They ſearched the Seriptures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo, and many of them believed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. The next Grace-begetting and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converting Ordinance, is frequent and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arneſt prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prayer is a fruit of faith, and yet prayer is a means for the begetting of faith; as the Spirit is the fruit of prayer, ſo prayer is the fruit of the Spirit, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 13. Compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15. In the former place, the Spirit is ſaid to be the fruit of prayer; in the latter place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prayer is ſaid to be the fruit of the Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we cry <hi>Abba Father, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 55. 6, 7. <hi>Seek the Lord whilſt he may be found, call upon him while he is neer, let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, &amp;c.</hi> James 1. 5. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdome, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him,</hi> Joh. 4. 10. <hi>Jeſus ſaid unto her, if thou kneweſt the gift of God, and who it is, that ſaith to thee, give me to drink, thou wouldſt have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Dwell much upon Grace-breeding, and ſoul converting promiſes, there are promiſes of direction, and ſupportation, and promiſes of protection, and promiſes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170385:36"/>
of juſtification, and ſanctification, and promiſes of acceptation; there are promiſes to ſettle us when we are wavering, and to ſupport us when we are falling, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call us when we are wandering, and to comfort us when we are fainting; ſurely, as the lamp liveth upon the oyle, and a child upon the breaſt; ſo doth faith upon the promiſes. All theſe and ſuch-like promiſes, are reduceable to theſe two heads, either abſolute, or conditional promiſes; The conditional promiſes runnes thus, <hi>Believe, and thou ſhall be ſaved,</hi> John 3. 16. <hi>Repent, and thy ſinnes ſhall be forgiven thee.</hi> The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute promiſes are ſuch, as are without condition, or ſuch wherein the Lord hath promiſed to give the condition, <hi>I will be merciful to your unrighteouſneſs, and your ſinnes and iniquities I will remember no more,</hi> Heb. 8. 12. So <hi>Iſa. 43. 25. I, even I am he, that blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out thy ſinnes for mine own ſake, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe, and ſuch abſolute promiſes, are Grace-breeding, or Faith-begetting pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. To theſe promiſes we muſt go for faith, to the conditional promiſes we muſt bring faith, without which we cannot apply them, but to the abſolute promiſes; we are not to bring our penny to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but go to them, as to the means of working faith in us, ſuch promiſes as theſe,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170385:37"/>
Jer. 32. 40. <hi>I will put my fear into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me,</hi> Ezek. 36. 25. <hi>I will ſprinkle water upon you, and you ſhall be clean from all your filthineſs,</hi> verſ. 26. <hi>A new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you.</hi> Verſ. 27. <hi>And cauſe you to walk in my wayes,</hi> Heb. 8. 12, <hi>For I will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſs, and their ſins and their iniquities, I will remember no more.</hi> Now let the Reader take one promiſe, and charge that upon the heart, and if the heart be ſtubborn, and will not yield, then take another, and if that will not do, take another, and lay that home upon the heart, and never leave this work, till you have gotten at leaſt ſome ſmall meaſure of faith. <hi>viz</hi> If thou doſt doubt, and canſt not believe the pardon of thy ſinnes, then take this promiſe, and charge it upon the heart, <hi>Iſa. 43. 25. I, even I am he, that blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out thy tranſgreſſions, for mine own ſake, and will not remember thy ſinnes:</hi> If the heart remain ſtubborn, and will not yield, then take another promiſe and charge that upon the heart, <hi>Mich. 7. 18, 19. Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the tranſgreſſion of his people? he retein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not his anger for ever, becauſe be delighteth in mercy, he will ſubdue our iniquities, and caſt all our ſinnes into the depth of the Seas.</hi> Now
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170385:37"/>
if the heart will not yield to believe this, then take that portion of Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 24. and bring it to the 53. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that whole Chapter, and charge that upon the heart, and there thou ſhalt finde, that our ſinnes <hi>were laid upon Chriſt, and the ſtripes due unto us for them, by which the Father is ſatisfied, the Law fulfilled, and by his ſtripes we are healed.</hi> Let us then believe and apply this, and we are ſaved; wherefore live much in the haven of the promiſes, feed upon the freeneſs, ſweetneſs and fatneſs thereof, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>God hath ſo far condeſcended to our weakneſs, for our eſtabliſhment, that he hath not only given us his promiſe, but promiſe upon promiſe, and aſſured us by the mouth of all his Prophets and Apoſtles, yea and Chriſt himſelf, that he is faithful, mindful, able and willing, and to this he gives us his covenant, his oath and his ſeale, and all to aſſure us he will never faile nor forſake us, but make good every tittle of his promiſe to us, How then can we look ſo many ſweet promiſes in the face, and harbour ſo many miſgivings in our hearts?</p>
               <p>3. The next meanes followeth, frequent the Company of Grace-begetting and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converting companions, where we ſhall hear how God hath wrought grace in them, and how the Lord doth uſually work
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170385:38"/>
upon the hearts of unbeleivers, as a man that cometh into a ſhop of perfumes, will carry away ſome of the ſent with him, ſo we with converſing with the godly ſhall be the better, Pro. 13. 20. <hi>he that walketh with wiſe men, ſhall be wiſer, but a companion of fools ſhall be deſtroyed;</hi> vaine talk and vaine practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, inticeth the minds of men to vanity, the noyſe of their fooliſh laughter, and ungodly diſcourſe, will drown the voice of conſcience, remember grace is hardly got, and hardly kept, and more hardly increaſed in ſuch company, Prov. 10. 20. 21. <hi>The tongue of the juſt, is as choice Silver, but the heart of the wicked is little worth, the lipps of the righteous feed many, but the fooliſh die for want of knowledge,</hi> Prov. 14. 7. <hi>Goe from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of fooliſh men, when thou perceiveſt not in him the lips of knowledg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Oh why ſhould we not ſtrive to live among thoſe companions on earth, that we muſt live with in heaven, if ever we come there? <hi>Nicodemus</hi> came to <hi>Jeſus</hi> for counſel, and Chriſt thereupon did give him adviſe in the great work of the new birth, So <hi>Math<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 19. 16. Another came and inquired <hi>what he ſhould do to be ſaved?</hi> ſo the Eunuch deſires inſtruction of <hi>Philip,</hi> Acts. 8. and <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Ananias,</hi> Acts. 9. 12. 13 17. and <hi>Cornelius</hi> inquired of <hi>Peter;</hi> ſo the Jews that were pricked at
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170385:38"/>
heart, askt <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>what they ſhould doe to be ſaved?</hi> Acts 2, 37. and the ſaylor asked <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, what he ſhould doe to be ſaved?</hi> To cloſe up this point, conſider this, that a man never goes in the company of wicked men, but he comes away, leſs a Chriſtian then he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Joſeph</hi> by this began to ſwear, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, life of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> being in bad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany but a little, began to ſwear and lye in one breath; therefore let us reſolve with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119. 63. to be <hi>a companion of all them that fear the Lord and keep his ſtatutes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then, if it be poſſible, frequent the company of the moſt ſober, ſerious, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, heavenly profeſſors, that will be drawing us heaven-ward, and opening to us the riches, freeneſſe, fulneſs, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingneſs of God the Fathers, and of the Sonnes love, and of the Holy Ghoſts love, one Lord bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>4. The next means for the begetting of grace, and converting the ſoul, may be this, let us meditate upon, and call to minde grace-begetting conſiderations, which may be reduceable to theſe few heads,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Conſider what Chriſt hath done for us,</item>
                  <item>2. Conſider how God hath dealt with other ſinners, as bad as we are.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170385:39"/>3. Conſider what relation we have to him.</item>
                  <item>4. Conſider what engagements we have from him.</item>
                  <item>5. Conſider in whoſe name we come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</item>
               </list>
               <p>1. Let us conſider what Chriſt hath done for us. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt by the will of God, gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a ranſom for our ſinnes, a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling favour, acceptable unto God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider that the Father accepted of this ſacrifice, in full ſatisfation for all our iniquities, tranſgreſſions and ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt, in the preaching of the Goſpel, doth make Proclamation with open mouth to all the world, that he, the Lord of Glory, is fully ſatisfied, foraſmuch as the debt, by Chriſt our ſurety, is fully paid; and the bond or hand writing that was againſt us, cancelled; and ſo much for the firſt Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, of what Chriſt hath done for us.</p>
               <p>2. Conſider, and that ſeriouſly, how God hath dealt with other ſinners as bad as we are, who have come to him, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord did not deſpiſe the weeping <hi>Mary,</hi> the begging <hi>Canaanite,</hi> the intreating <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican,</hi> the confeſſing <hi>Thief,</hi> the adulterous,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170385:39"/>
                  <hi>Woman,</hi> the denying <hi>Diſciple,</hi> the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c. And if he refuſed not theſe, but ſhewed mercy to them, converting and healing them, he will not reject me, if 1 ariſe and go to him, <hi>Pſal. 119. 59. I thought on my waies, and turned my feet to thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, I made haſt, and delayed not to keep thy commandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. Conſider what relation we have to him, he is our Creator, we are his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; in a word, we are his by right of Creation, Redemption, and now we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be his by right of Regeneration, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Marriage, and Covenant &amp;c.</p>
               <p>4. Conſider what engagements we have from him, <hi>viz.</hi> he hath promiſed to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our ſinnes, to purge our natures, <hi>Ezek. 36. 25. Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean from all your filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. Conſider in whoſe name we come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, not in our own, neither in the name of any, but only his own dear Son, <hi>in whom he is well pleaſed,</hi> and for his ſake he hath promiſed, that whatſoever we ask in his Name he will give it unto us. 1. We have his prayer to the Father, to <hi>ſubdue and conquer our luſts,</hi> John 17. 17. 2. We have his promiſe, <hi>I will ſubdue your iniquities,</hi> Micah. 17. 19. <hi>Sin ſhall have no more domin ion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170385:40"/>
over you,</hi> Rom. 6. 14. 3. He is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Redeemer, but alſo a Refiner, a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, he gave himſelf for us, to redeem us from all iniquity, and to cleanſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie us to be his peculiar people, zealous of good works. 4. We have his merits, as a Sanctuary to fly unto, as to a fountain ſet open to waſh us, from all finne, filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and uncleanneſs, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13. 1. Sure theſe are grace breeding conſiderations, conſider them over and over again and again.</p>
               <p>5. The fifth means is, gather and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure up a ſtock of Grace-begetting and Soul-converting experiences; <hi>viz.</hi> We have had ſome experience of the riches, freeneſs, fulneſs, and everlaſtingneſs of Gods love, and we have a little taſte of the ſufficiency and efficacy of the death and ſufferings of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. 27. O friends, ſhall <hi>Laban,</hi> a natural man, make uſe of experience which he had treaſured up, and ſhall not a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, in carrying on the work of grace, began in his ſoul, make uſe of it much more? It is the duty, and it ſhould be the practiſe of all in converting, and alſo of thoſe converted, to treaſure up experiences of Gods goodneſs to them, even from their cradles, that God made them men, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170385:40"/>
women, and not toads and ſerpents, that he hath hitherto preſerved them, when he might have deſtroyed them, that they have as yet the means of grace, whilſt others in the world want, that they have liberty, ſight, limbs, food and raiment; theſe and ſuch like are the bleſſings of his left hand, and he tenders to thee alſo the bleſſings of his right hand, <hi>Pſal. 63. 7. Becauſe thou haſt been my help, therefore in the ſhaddow of thy wings will I rejoyce, 2 Cor. 1. 10. Who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver us, in whom we truſt be will yet deliver us,</hi> See <hi>Pſal. 116. 2. Becauſe be hath inclined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live.</hi> It is good to hear, better to hear and underſtand, better to enjoy, and beſt of all to have bleſſed experience of what we hear, underſtand and enjoy; the Saints of old could ſay, that they had ſuch experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the faithfulneſſe of the Lord, that he made good every thing that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them, no one good thing failed, <hi>Joſh. 21. 45. There failed not any good thing, that the Lord had promiſed to the houſe of Iſrael, all came to paſſe, Joſh. 23. 14. Not ſo much as one thing hath failed, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the uſe of theſe and the like meanes, the Lord uſually ſcattereth ſome little ſeeds of grace in the hearts of thoſe that he will
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170385:41"/>
bring unto himſelf, which ſeeds being ſowen, doe afterwards by degrees put forth, and act towards God, as we may ſee in <hi>Lydia,</hi> the <hi>Jaylor,</hi> and <hi>Zacheus</hi> &amp;c. God makes himſelf known to us as a God of mercy, gracious, long-ſuffering, pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iniquitie, tranſgreſſion and ſin, and ſo offers himſelf to be reconciled to us, though we have rebelled againſt him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to be a Father unto us, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of us in his beloved, as his ſons and daughters, and thus is the difference made up between God and man; the ſoul begins now to ſay, at leaſt in its ſelf, I that was an enemy, he hath now reconciled unto himſelf; I that was in times paſt without God, without Chriſt, without promiſe, without covenant, without hope, yet now I have God for my God, he is become my ſalvation, Chriſt is become my Redeermer, the Holy Ghoſt my Sanctifier. O bleſſed, thrice bleſſed be Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt! O how often did he call, how carneſtly did he knock, how powerfully did he ſtrive, how long did he wait upon me, before my ſtubborn hard heart would yield? if he had never loved me, I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver loved him; if he had never drawn me, I had never come; if he had never ſought me, I had been yet ſtraying in the wilderneſs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170385:41"/>
of iniquitie, and feeding in the fields of vanity; now I ſee that God keeps open houſe, invites, intreate, beſeecheth us to beleive, and come in, <hi>O every one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters, come buy ye that have no Silver or Gold, come buy milk and wine without money,</hi> Iſai<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 55, 1. and <hi>he that comes to me.</hi> John 6. 37. <hi>I will in no wiſe cast out.</hi> Let him that will, come, whoſoever hath a mind let him come, let his ſinnes be what they will be, for nature, number, and for continuance, yet come, I will in no wiſe caſt thee off, <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, &amp; paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion, of the remnant of his heritage, thou retaineſt not anger for ever, for thou delightest to ſhow mercy,</hi> Micah 7. 18, 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Means to be uſed for the confirming, ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ratifying, and increaſing of Grace, where it is began.</head>
               <p>WEe are to take notice, that the ſame meanes for the moſt part, that doth beget or breed grace in us, doth build up, nouriſh and increaſe the ſame; theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned means, are both the begetters and the nouriſhers, both the breeders and feeders of grace, <hi>viz.</hi> Hearing the Word
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170385:42"/>
preached, reading the Word, prayer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, good company, conſiderations, and choice experiences; all theſe are full to nouriſh and ſtrengthen grace; alſo the Sacraments were inſtituted and ſet up for this end, to increaſe our grace, and aſſure us of the pardon of our ſinnes, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our ſoules; Baptiſme is a ſeal of our entrance into the Church of God, the Supper of the Lord is a ſeal of our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in the ſame; the former is a ſeal of our new birth, the latter is a ſeal of our ſpiritual growth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; in Baptiſme, ſome of our ſenſes are exerciſed, in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, all our ſenſes are or ought to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; this Ordinance is to be uſed often, baptiſm but once; for these is but one entrance into Chriſt, but there are many degrees of growth in him. Again, Conſider that we are to wait on God in the uſe of means frequently; as we muſt not forſake our meals for our bodies, ſo we are not to neglect our meals for our ſouls, cut not off religious exerciſes too ſhort, turn not theſe holy duties into matter of faſhion or form, but come with an hungry appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; and that thou maiſt ſo do, dip thy morſels often in the ſharp ſawce, and ſowr herb of humiliation; look back and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what once thou waſt. Now, though
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170385:42"/>
we grant that the Miniſtery of the Word, whether Law or Goſpel, is but as it were a dead letter, and profiteth little without the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 7. Neither is he that planteth any thing, nor he that watereth, but God that giveth the increaſe,</hi> We cannot prevail with the blind to ſee, nor with the deaf to hear, or with the dead to live; yet are we with diligence to attend upon God in the uſe of means, for though the means cannot work without the Spirit, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ordinarily will not work without the means; Man is a reaſonable creature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God proceedeth with him by way of arguments or means; but becauſe man in ſome ſenſe, is a dead creature, therefore he muſt work in him, that which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades him to; he commandeth us who are unwilling, to be willing, and then by the powerful efficacy of the Spirit, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the will of unwillingneſs, he makes us willing; By the firſt he <hi>stands at the door and knocks,</hi> Rev. 3. 20. By the ſecond, he <hi>opens the door, and comes in, and ſups with us;</hi> He in his Word calls upon us, to will and to do; the Spirit of Chriſt worketh in us, both to will and to do; God in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſpake the word, that ſuch a creature ſhould be, and therewithal ſent forth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower cauſing that creature to be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170385:43"/>
to his word. So whilſt the Angel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth unto <hi>Mary</hi> the conception of Chriſt, the power of the Holy Ghoſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed her, whence it was with her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 35, 38. So alſo whilſt <hi>Jeſus cried with a loud voice,</hi> John 11. 43, 44. <hi>Lazarus come forth;</hi> there proceeded from him a power whereby he came forth. So <hi>Luke</hi> 5 24. He commanded the man that was ſick of the palſie, <hi>to take up his bed and walk,</hi> and conveyes a power together with the command, whereby verſ. 25 <hi>He did immediately ariſe, took up his bed, and went to his houſe and glorified God,</hi> So again, <hi>Ezek. 2. 1, 2. And he ſaid unto me, Son of man, ſtand upon thy feet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I will ſpeak unto thee, and the Spirit entered into me when he ſpake, and ſet me upon my feet, and I heard him that ſpake unto me, &amp;c.</hi> But in the uſe of theſe and the like precious means, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe cautions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be ſure that the means you make uſe of, be means of Gods own appointment, of his own providing, to which he hath annexed his promiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider, it is not the means ſingly that helps, but Gods bleſſing upon the means, without which, the moſt likely means, bringeth nothing to paſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider his bleſſing is diſpenſed, not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170385:43"/>
ſo much according to the means, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the uprightneſſe of the heart, in the uſe of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, notwithſtanding all this, we are to wait upon God in the uſe of them frequently, as it is Gods way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance; for where ordinary means may do, he will not uſe extraordinary.</p>
               <p>The walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> muſt fall, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 6. from verſ. 4. to ver. 15. but they muſt uſe the means, although but weak means, that we might not ſlight the means. So <hi>John</hi> 9. from the 1. verſe to the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, when our Saviour opened the eyes of the man that was born blind, <hi>He made clay of ſpittle and annointed the eyes of the blind man, and bid him go waſh in the pool of Siloam, and be went and waſhed, and came ſeeing.</hi> So the ſtone muſt be rowled from <hi>Lazarus</hi> grave, and <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt <hi>ſinite the rock</hi> to get water for the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> all which are written for our learning, to ingage us to be diligent in the uſe of means, and preſents us with our duty, <hi>viz.</hi> that we ſhould leave no means unattempted, for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what God hath promiſed; for the means are Gods pipes of conveyance; which if we cut off, how can we expect the things we want, which God hath promiſed to give? Chriſt did not diſcharge us from
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170385:44"/>
the debt of ſinne, to free us from the debt of ſervice; but therefore he did pay the one, that we might wait upon him in the uſe of the other; he that withdraws himſelf from the promiſe, cannot long keep cloſe to the precept, and he that keeps at a diſtance from the uſe of means, ſhall never attain the mercies conveyed to others therein.</p>
               <p>The Sacraments were inſtituted and ſet up for this very end, to increaſe and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſeal and eſtabliſh us; the Lord knew he had to deal with doubting, ſtaggering, miſgiving perſons, and therefore he doth not only give the promiſe, his covenant and oath, for the confirmation of us, but to all theſe he annexeth his ſeal, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper. Here I ſhall give the Reader a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the ſum and ſubſtance of what hitherto in this Treatiſe hath been preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo proceed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We have began with mans creation, and of his eſtate before he fell, &amp; of the manner of his fall, and the ſubtilty of Satan therein, and of the miſerable eſtate he fell into, and how he can never be ſaved, unleſs born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, renewed and reſtored; there are four Gates ſhut, and five exceptions made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; there be amongſt the Sons and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170385:44"/>
Daughters of men, eighteen ſorts, that ſhall not either ſee, nor enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; there be four ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why he will execute juſtice upon them; there are four ſorts of changes, and but one of them ſpiritual and ſaving; Man is in miſery, and unable and unwilling to help himſelf out, &amp;c. Of the preparations or qualifications that we are to find in our ſelves, before we lay hold on Chriſt and the promiſe; Converſion and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Vocation and Repentance, are but four words to hold forth, as it were, one and the ſelf ſame thing: Of the way ſtep by ſtep how the Lord in his ordinary diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in theſe Goſpel-dayes, doth lead a ſoul, as it were, by the hand, out of a ſtate of nature into a ſtate of grace; Firſt, by enlightning the ſoul; Secondly, by calling him effectually; Thirdly, by enabling him to believe; Fourthly, by giving him the ſpirit of prayer, by which he prayes for more light to ſee his ſins, and then for pardoning mercy, and for purging mercy; Fifthly, the Lord doth cauſe the ſoul ſecretly to give it ſelf up to God, and ſo he comes to ſurrender all its own ſuppoſed intereſt that he had in himſelf, unto God that made it, and unto Chriſt that hath dearly purchaſed it; then there follweth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170385:45"/>
the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be uſed, to breed and beget grace, and to convert the ſoul; Firſt to keep cloſe to grace-begetting Ordinances, <hi>viz.</hi> hearing the Word preached, reading the Scriptures, and frequent and earneſt prayer; Secondly, to dwell much upon grace-begetting promiſes; Thirdly, to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the company of grace-begetting and ſoul-converting companions; Fourthly, to call to mind, and meditate upon grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begetting conſiderations; Fiſthly, to gather and to treaſure up grace-begetting and ſoul-converting experiences, and ſo to be diligent in the uſe of many other means, for the confirming, ſealing, and aſſuring the ſoul of ſalvation; theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubordinate branches, thou haſt here preſented, in a little room, and a few words, &amp;c. Now to proceed a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in this great work, and ſo to draw towards a cloſe, let the Reader conſider theſe things following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. If we remain in an unconverted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, let us blame our ſelves only; for the want of converſion is not in God, for he makes uſe of all means, and wayes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We ſhall preſent the Reader with ſome of the principal hinderances of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170385:45"/>3. Conſider the ſad and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the unconverted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The trials of converſion, by which a man may know, whether he be converted, yea, or no</p>
               <p n="5">5. The priviledges, and benefits of all that are converted.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Certain Objections anſwered, which ſome out of weakneſs, and others out of prejudice, may be apt to make againſt the foregoing diſcourſe, and ſo I ſhall cloſe up this Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The want of Converſion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not in God, but in our ſelves, he makes uſe of all means and waies to convert us.</head>
               <p>1. Our converſion and ſalvation is not a thing impoſſible, for a new and living way is conſecrated for us by Chriſt, through the vail, his fleſh, and by his blood we may have boldneſs to enter into the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt, he hath borne our burthen, he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the impoſſibilities, and nailed to his Croſs the hand-writing that was againſt us, <hi>Coll.</hi> 2. 14, 15. So that if any of us periſh, it is for want of grace in us, not for want of ſatisfaction by the Redeemer: ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is brought even to our doors, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170385:46"/>
thruſt in as it were into our hands; we have Chriſt himſelf offered us, and pardon, life and ſalvation with him, we have God himſelf waiting to be gracious, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching us to be reconciled to him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19, 20. We have the Lords Embaſſadors intreating us in his Name and ſtead; the Lord hath provided excellent and plentiful means, with promiſe upon promiſe of his preſence with, and bleſſing upon us in the uſe of them, and if the Spirit make not theſe means effectual, it will not be long of him, but of our ſelves, God himſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents and offereth us mercy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 23. and continues his Ordinance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; the Angels waits for the joy that is due to them upon our converſion; Miniſters are preaching and praying for our converſion, godly friends and neighbours are praying and longing to ſee this work wrought in us, See Mr. <hi>Bax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers Call to the unconverted, in the Preface;</hi> We ſtudy plainneſs of ſpeach to make them underſtand, we come with ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous piercing words, to make them feel, but they will neither underſtand nor feel; if the greateſt matters would work with them, we ſhould awake them, if the ſweeteſt things would work, we ſhould intice them, if the moſt dreadful things would work, we ſhould affright them, if truth and certainty
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170385:46"/>
would take with them, we ſhould ſoon convince them, if the God that made them, and the Chriſt that bought them, might be heard, the caſe would ſoon be altered with them, if Scripture might be heard, we ſhould ſoon prevail, if the beſt and ſtrongeſt reaſon might be heard, we ſhould ſpeedily convince them, if experience might be heard, even their own experience, the matter would ſoon be mended; yea if the conſcience within them might be heard, the caſe would ſoon be better with them than it is, but if the dreadful God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven be ſlighted, who then ſhall be regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? If the blood of a Redeemer be made ſlight of, what then ſhall be valued? If the joyes of Heaven is not worth the deſiring, and the torments of Hell the avoiding, what ſhall we do for ſuch ſouls as theſe &amp;c? Now if after all theſe and the like means Man will not turn, it is not long of God that they are not converted, but of themſelves; ſo that Mans deſtruction is of himſelf, <hi>James</hi> 1. 15. So earneſt is God for the converſion of ſinners, that he dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth his commands and exhortations <hi>Turn ye, turn ye, why will ye dy,</hi> Ezek. 33. 11. Again, it is the promiſe of God, that the wicked ſhall live, if they will but turn, nay, the Lord hath confirmed it to us by an
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170385:47"/>
oath, <hi>That he hath no pleaſure in the death of the wicked,</hi> See the forementioned place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 11. Nay farther, the Lord condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to reaſon the cauſe with all unconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinners, as to ask them why they will dy in their ſinnes, See the forementioned place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 11. Compared with 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 9. The Lord is long-ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some of the principal hinderances of Converſion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt Hindrance, is ignorance both of their own miſery, and Gods mercy; the kingdome of Satan is a kingdome of darkneſs, and himſelf the ruler of darkneſs, and the <hi>miſt and blackneſs of darkneſs is reſerved to him and his ſervants for ever,</hi> Jude 6, 13. compared with John. 3. 19. <hi>this is condemnation, that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather than light:</hi> So that if the Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the God of this world, hath blinded the minds of them that believe not, leſt the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine unto them; but thoſe that are converted, can truly ſay, <hi>we were once darkneſs, but now we are light in the Lord,</hi> Ephes 5. 8.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170385:47"/>2. Hindrance of converſion is, men think it to be either an eaſie work, or a needleſs work.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It cannot be an eaſie work: Jer. 13. 23. <hi>Can the Aethiopian change his ſkin, and the Leopard his ſpots, then may they that are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to do evil, learn to do well.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not a needleſs work, but one of the moſt needfulleſt works, without which we periſh everlaſtingly in Hell, John. 3. 3. 5. Mat. 18. 3. <hi>except a man be born again, be cannot ſee the kingdom of God, and except ye be converted and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of Heaven:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Hindrance, is either a total neglect, or a careleſs formal uſe of thoſe ordinary meanes which God hath appointed, for the breeding and perfecting the work of converſion; if we will not eat, how can we live and grow? if we will not drink, how can we quench our thirſt? if we will not wear cloathes, how can we be warm? if vve vvill not ſovve and plant, hovv can vve reap? ſhall vve be induſtrious and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect no means for the obteining of natural things, and altogether remiſs in the uſe of means for the obtaining of ſpiritual, that are far better? ſurely we ought to leave no means unattempted for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of what God hath promiſed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170385:48"/>
we have more commands and promiſes for the latter, than we have for the former.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hindrance is, mens not confidering the joyes of Heaven, and the torments of Hell, that ſo the love of the one might win them, or the fear of the other compell them to make uſe of the means, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their talent and time, for the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of life and ſalvation, and the eſcaping of Hell and damnation; ſurely we ought to lay aſide every weight, and the ſin that doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and <hi>to run with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the race that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus the author and finiſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, indured the croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame,</hi> Heb. 12. 1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hindrance is, falſe conceits, that they are converted already; which ariſeth from ſome ſeeming change in an external con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Goſpel, which ariſeth from the ſouls ſight of fin, and ſenſe of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which leads him ſo far as to confeſs his fins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 4. and vomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it up, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 20. and in ſome good meaſure, abſtain from the external commiſſion of it, and ſo reformeth its converſation; ignorance is taken away by illumination; pleaſure in fin is abated, by ſorrow for fin, boldneſs in finning is abated, by the fear of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: he may know the very time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170385:48"/>
ſermon, the book, the chapter, the verſe, that were the means of doing this work, and therefore thinks it is truly done, and that he hath a ſaving change, and yet it may be but common preparation, or ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon works, which many partake of that periſh, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Hindrance, is, too deep a familiarity with bad company, Oh what a dangerous thing it is to live amongſt ſuch company, as will be ſtill hindring, but never helping in the way to heaven, <hi>who can converſe with defiled ones, and not be defiled?</hi> Pſal. 106. 35. the people were <hi>mingled amongſt the heathen, and learned their works.</hi> Pſal. 119. 115. evil doers we muſt depart from, if ever we keep the commands of God, theſe are not grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begetting, and ſoul-converting, but grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hindring, and ſoul-condemning compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Hindrance, is their ignorance of the principles of Religion, their not being Catechiſed themſelves, neither catechiſing their Families: ſo that the foundational truths, are for the moſt part Paradoxes and Riddles to them.</p>
               <p>8. Hindrance, is Delay; when men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to become new men, and to live ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, and to leave ſin, and to take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe, yet they delay and put off the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170385:49"/>
time till the next year, and when that is come, to the laſt moneth of that year, and when that is come, to the laſt vveek of that moneth, and vvhen that is come, to the laſt day of that vveek, and when that is come, to the laſt hour of that day, and when that is come, to the laſt minute of that hour, and ſo in the mean while they are <hi>hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin,</hi> as Heb. 3. 13. and ſo goe on from folly to folly, until they are ripe for eternal miſery: Oh! ſay they, we are yet young, and have day-light and time enough; we are yet in health and there is no ſuch haſte: and thus many are cut off, whilſt they are purpoſing to return; and many thouſand ſouls are loſt, as it is to be feared, that once were purpoſed to have turned to God before they die, and all by delaying and continuing in ſinning, til they have ſinned themſelves into a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe, and ſo they muſt periſh everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, by delaying to make uſe of their remedie, by not <hi>calling upon God whilſt he was near, and ſeeking him whilſt he might be found:</hi> See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 6. compared with <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 24. 28. I might inſtance in many other hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances, as hardneſs of heart, unbelief, love of this preſent evil world, the Differences amongſt Profeſſors; but I cannot ſpeak par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to them all, leſt this Book ſhould ſvvell too bigg.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170385:49"/>
               <head>Of the ſad condition of all that are not Converted.</head>
               <p>THe longer men or women ſtay, or go on, in an unconverted eſtate, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is their ſin, the harder is their cure, and the greater will be their puniſhment, &amp;c. They make void as much as in them lyeth, the great Counſel of God, and all the thoughts of his wiſdom, in contriving ſuch a way to advance his own glory, in the ſalvation of man; Yea, they make void all the purpoſes of Gods mercy to them, in reſtoring and renewing them, and ſending Chriſt to die for them; yea they do as much as in them lyeth, make void the death of Chriſt, they make all his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and blood-ſhed, to be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. You deny him that which is his own, you deny him your hearts and ſouls, that which he hath made and redeemed; you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him that which none can lay claim to, but himſelf; again they are curſed in their going out and coming in, in their basket and in their ſtore, and in all they put their hands unto, they can do nothing truly pleaſing to God, but are ſervants, and ſlaves to Satan, and led about as his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives at his will, and ſo remain in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170385:50"/>
danger of damnation, there being but a breath between them and Hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the priviledges, and benefits of all that are Converted</head>
               <p>THe Lord is their portion, and they are the Lords portion, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 9. what ever loſſes, croſſes, troubles and trials, they may paſs through here, all ſhall work for their good at the preſent, and they ſhall be freed from all troubles in time to come, there was joy in Heaven at their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 10.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Chriſt calls them his ſervants, <hi>John</hi> 12. 26.</item>
                  <item>2. Again, he calls them his friends, <hi>John</hi> 15. 15.</item>
                  <item>3. He calls them his brethren, <hi>Mar.</hi> 3. 34.</item>
                  <item>4. He calls them his Jewels or treaſure, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 17.</item>
                  <item>5. He calls them his ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 18.</item>
                  <item>6. He calls them the Bride, the Lambs wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 9.</item>
                  <item>7. He calls them co-heirs with himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And if all this be too little to expreſs his heart to them, then he tells them, that the Father loveth them with the ſame love,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170385:50"/>
(for the quality of it) wherewith he loveth Chriſt; what ſhall I ſay more? they have the glory of God to be their aime, the word to be their rule, the ſpirit to be their guide, the angels to be their guard, and the bleſſed promiſes to be their ſupport, and as by vertue of their oneneſs with the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> his ſin was made theirs; ſo by vertue of their oneneſs with the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> his righteouſneſs is made theirs; nay farther, they have by vertue of converting grace, union with Chriſt, and ſo communion with the life and Spirit of Chriſt, with the death and ſufferings of Chriſt, with the merits and victories of Chriſt, with the priviledges and immunities, as Adoption, Son-ſhip, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The trials of Converſion by which a man may know whether he be converted yea or no.</head>
               <p>LEt the Reader make a curious, narrow, impartial, diligent ſearch into his own ſoul, and ſee what humility, what ſelf-denial, what ſin-abhorrancy, what love to Chriſt, what delight in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, what zeal for Gods glory, what contempt of the world, what deſiring after the ſociety of the Saints, what ſympathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170385:51"/>
in their afflictions; and if thou findeſt any impreſſions of grace, any ſpiritual work, any ſaving, ſavoury diſtinguiſhing operation upon thy ſoul, and heart, then the Spirit hath been there with his cure, and thou art as certainly born again, as thou waſt born firſt; but theſe graces thus planted in the heart, at firſt are full of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, there is ſome darkneſs with your light, ſome enmity with your love, much hardneſs of heart with your mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin, and much worldly ſorrow in your pureſt tears, much pride with your humility, much murmuring with your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and therefore great care is to be taken, in the laying down theſe trials, or marks of converſion, for as we are to put a difference, between gifts and grace, and internal and external marks and ſigns, ſo alſo we are to diſtinguiſh between thoſe that are ſtrong in grace, and thoſe that are weak in grace, that have but little grace, and this will be of great uſe to Chriſtians that are but of a lower forme; new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, having but little grace, yet they may know that little they have, though as yet they have not attained ſtrength of grace, yet they may know the truth of grace in themſelves, although they come ſhort of ſtrong believers, yet they ſhall know they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170385:51"/>
go beyond the moſt ſhining hypocrite; for the leaſt meaſure of grace, is better than the greateſt meaſure of gifts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But we come to the trials of the new birth, by which a man may know whether he is born again, yea or no.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He that is truly converted, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the word and means of grace, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.</item>
                  <item>2. He is either willing, or willing to be made willing to do whatſoever the Lord doth command him, though it be never ſo contrary to fleſh and blood, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 16.</item>
                  <item>3. He is brought unto an unſeined ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the whole body of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. compared with, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. 21.</item>
                  <item>4. His greateſt and hotteſt mournings and ſtrivings is againſt his inward polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his cloſe, ſpiritual and ſecret ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 12. compared with, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 8.</item>
                  <item>5. He often mourns for the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for the want of growth in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Lam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 16. &amp; 3. 48.</item>
                  <item>6. He doth love to be ſpeaking of thoſe great and ſaving truths, which his heart hath taken in, in the work of converſion.</item>
                  <item>7. He doth begin to keep a watch over his own heart.</item>
                  <item>8. He makes conſcience of keeping every known command.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170385:52"/>9. He is willing to put himſelf upon the tryal, and to have any Chriſtian ſearch him, and ſometimes he intreats the Lord to ſearch him. <hi>Pſal. 139. 23. Lam.</hi> 3. 40.</item>
                  <item>10. He that is born again, or truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h his ſoul renewed in its faculties and vertues, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are ſuch flowers of Paradiſe, that grows not in Natures garden, until the new man was put on, and the party renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſpirit of his mind, until Chriſt was formed in him; for theſe are pearls that are not to be found in the worlds field: wherefore we ſhall ſpeak ſomething to each of them briefly; but before I proceed further, let me give the Reader this cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Let not every one think he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, unleſs he finde theſe and the like characters of a true converſion in him, if he finde but ſomething of every thing, if it be but in the budding, in the breeding, in the beginning, his ſtate may be good; for when he is a well grown Chriſtian, theſe things will more and more clearly appear, at the firſt converſion a man hath as it were but the root of them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He that is indeed born againe, and ſo converted, doth deſire the word and means of grace, 1 Pet. 2. 2. <hi>as new born babes deſire
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170385:52"/>
the ſincere milk of the word, that they may grow thereby.</hi> There the apoſtle makes it a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of a ſpiritual man; a man ſpiritually new born will deſire after the meanes of grace, that he may grow in grace; by milk, is here meant the word of God, which is compared to milk, Firſt becauſe of the ſweetneſs of it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 10. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 103. Secondly becauſe of the purity of it, it is without falſhood, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 18. and 119. 140, and Thirdly becauſe of the nouriſhing property thereof, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16, 17. When the Lord begets one by the immortal ſeed of his word, he teacheth him to reſt upon the word of promiſe which indureth for ever, tendred in the Goſpel; indeed tho whole word of God is ſincere milk where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we grow, and the old and new Teſtament may be called the Breſts of conſolation; but if we grow not, it is becauſe we feed not, we play with the breaſt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that is indeed born againe, he is either willing, or at leaſt willing that the Lord ſhould make him willing, to obſerve and do whatſoever the Lord doth command him, though it be never ſo contrary to fleſh and blood, Acts. 9. 9. <hi>Lord what will thou have me to do?</hi> How willing <hi>Paul</hi> was to lay down his firſt commiſſion, &amp; to take up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>10. 3, <hi>thy people ſhall be willing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170385:53"/>
in the day of thy power.</hi> They are willing to hear, ſpeak Lord, for thy ſervant heareth; they are willing to do, Lord what wilt thou have me to do, <hi>Pſal. 119. 5. Oh that my waies were directed to keep thy ſtatutes.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>David</hi> ſets down another character of a godly man, <hi>Pſal. 1. 2. His delight is in the Law of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> after conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſpeaks of himſelf, that his delight was in the Law of God, as concerning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, So again in another <hi>Pſal. 40. 8. I delight to do thy will, thy Law is in my hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> there was a principal within him agreeable to the precept without him, this is a clear demonſtration of a new creature, though he may drive heavily, ſometimes under vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and laſting temptations.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that is effectually converted, he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought unto an unfeined hatred of the whole body of ſin, eſpecially his beloved ſins, that did moſt powerfully captivate him before, <hi>Col. 3. 7, 8. But now you put off all theſe, anger, wrath, malice, blaſphemy, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy communication,</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 6. 11. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 3, 4, 5. &amp;c. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he hath an unfeined hatred of the whole body of ſin, as it is the greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in the world; ſin is worſe than hell, there may be good in puniſhment, but there can be no good in ſin, it makes God
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170385:53"/>
                  <hi>hide his face from us,</hi> and ſhut out our prayers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 2. it is <hi>the cauſe of all wars,</hi> James 4. 1. it is the <hi>cauſe of all ſickneſs,</hi> Deut. 28. In a word, ſin is the cauſe of all miſery, both temporal, ſpiritual, and eternal, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Daniel</hi> was content to be thrown into the den of Lyons, rather than to ſin, the three Children in the fire, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> into the priſon, and many Chriſtians have choſen to imbrace priſons, ſtakes, fire, and the hotteſt perſecutions rather than ſin, a converted perſon comes to ſee the weakneſs and wickedneſs of his own heart, he knows he cannot truſt any member alone without a guard.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He that is indeed converted may know it by this, <hi>viz.</hi> his greateſt and hotteſt conflicts are againſt inward pollution, his cloſe, ſpiritual, and ſecret ſins, that are known only to God and himſelf; he doth accuſe himſelf for that which no man can accuſe him, he blames himſelf for that which no man can blame him, he judgeth and arraigneth himſelf for that which no man can judge him for, he makes a through and ſound ſearch, he knows Hypocriſie is ſpun of a fine thred, and is not diſcerned without diligent ſearch: Again, he knows that one ſtab at the heart, though it be with a pen-knife, will kill a man, one little
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170385:54"/>
leak in a Ship will ſink it, and one ſecret ſin unrepented of, will damn a Soul, the leaſt ſin contains in it the nature of all ſin; no ſooner did one ſin enter into <hi>Adams</hi> heart but he had all ſin in him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He often mourns for the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and for the want of more grace in himſelf, we read <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 17. that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>did weep in ſecret places for the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> ſo in another place, <hi>mine eyes run down with tears, becauſe men keep not thy laws<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> and as for the ſins of others, ſo for the want of more grace in themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah 6. 5. <hi>I am a man of unclean lips</hi> ſaid <hi>Iſaiah. I abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes</hi> ſaid <hi>Job,</hi> Job. 42 6 <hi>Surely I am more brutiſh than any man, and have not the knowledge of a man,</hi> ſaid <hi>Augur,</hi> Pro. 30. 2. <hi>I am leſs than the least of all Saints</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul,</hi> Eph. 3. 8. nay I have ſo little grace, that I am the greateſt of Sinners, 1 Tim. 1. 15 <hi>Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. He doth dearly love to be ever now and then ſpeaking of thoſe great and ſaving truths, which his heart took in the work of converſion, he feeleth moſt ſavour of life in thoſe neceſſary points which were inſtruments of this bleſſed change that there is made upon him, and upon theſe he feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th and delighteth, even on the inward
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170385:54"/>
life of ſpiritual things, and ſo he feedeth his hungry Soul, in hearing and reading, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and converſing with Chriſtians; he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to learn ſomething from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>very thing.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He doth begin to keep a watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his own heart, eyes, and tongue and feet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He keeps his heart with <hi>Solomons</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He keeps his eyes with <hi>Jobs</hi> Covenant, <hi>Job.</hi> 31. 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He keeps his tongue with <hi>Davids</hi> bridle, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 39. 7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He keeps his foot with <hi>Solomons</hi> guard, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 1. In a word, we ſhould not truſt any Member, without its Keeper, for there doth and will remain, even in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted themſelves, the remnants of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a body of death, a rebelling fleſh, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be ſtill tempting and draw them from God, ſo that the whole way to Heaven is a continual warfare; there be enemies that will diſpute every foot of the way, there is no going a ſtep forward, but as the ſhip doth in the Sea, by cutting its way through the waves: there is Self our greateſt enemy, and there is Sathan and the world, and almoſt all that we meet with in it, will prove hinderances in the way to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170385:55"/>
Heaven, therefore keep up your watch with your loynes girt, and your lamps burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He that is truly converted makes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of keeping every known duty or command, in reſpect of the general bent and frame of his heart he doth ſubject himſelf to Chriſt freely, univerſally, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and unweariedly, at leaſt in deſire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if it be not ſo, he could wiſh it were ſo, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours &amp; prays to have it ſo, he conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that Chriſt did not diſcharge us from the debt of ſin, to free us from the debt of ſervice, but therefore did he pay the one, that we might be able to return the other. <hi>Rom. 8. 12. Therefore we are Debters not to the ſleſh,</hi> 1 John 2. 5. <hi>Who ſo keepeth his word, in him is the love of God perfected: hereby know we that we are in him;</hi> there is no known ſin but he labours to avoid, and no known grace but he longs to have, and no known duty but he labours to perform.</p>
               <p n="9">9. He is willing to put himſelf upon the tryal, whether he be converted or no, he is willing to have any Chriſtian to ſearch him, and ſometimes he entreats the Lord to ſearch him, he loves thoſe company beſt that deals moſt plainly with him, he care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and continually ſearcheth himſelf, and goes down with light into his heart, he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170385:55"/>
is jealous of his own heart, he doubts of none more than himſelf, ſuſpects moſt his own graces, and the witneſſe of his own ſpirit, leaſt Sathan ſhine like an Angel of light, and ſay it is the teſtimony of Gods ſpirit, he is content to have his ſpiritual eſtate tryed by any, not only by a ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſtry in publick, but by any private Friends; he opens his heart freely for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ask, and gives anſwers of his hope with weakneſſe and fear, his ears are open to the whole word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he believes the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and trembles, he fears alſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, leſt he comes ſhort, he hath found out the hell in his heart, and feels the flames of it in ſecret, he hath found an emptineſs in himſelf, and an enmity to all good, he is poor in ſpirit, which appears by his continual complaints, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunat prayers, he deſireth not to be found in his own righteouſneſs, but in Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, all the reſt he accounts as dung.</p>
               <p n="10">10. He that is born again, or truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, hath his ſoul renewed in its facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and vertues, when the Lord made man in his own image <hi>Gen. 1. 26, 27. Gen.</hi> 9. 6. which image of God in man conſiſteth not in any bodily ſhape, but in the nature of the ſoul, as it is a ſpiritual and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſubſtance, indued with three faculties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170385:56"/>
Underſtanding, Will and Memory, as the Deitie hath three, Father, Sonne and Holy Ghoſt, this image of God in man, by his fall was defaced, which by regeneration is again reſtored and renewed.</p>
               <p>1. In its faculties. 2. In its ſenſes. 3 In its vertues.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>1. In its faculties,</head>
                  <item>1. Underſtanding.</item>
                  <item>2. Will.</item>
                  <item>3. Memory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The Underſtanding, that by the fall was darkened, is now again by regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nlightened, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 8. Compared with <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Will that was inthralled, is now renewed, by which it doth chooſe the good, and reject the evil.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Memory, that ſince the fall of Man would forget the good that it ſhould have reteyned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and retein the evill that it ſhould forget, is now reſtored, ſo as to treaſure up ſpiritual things, and let ſlip car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal things.</p>
               <p>The Conſcience, which is Gods Deputy in man, that did ceaſe to do his Office <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeared with an hot Iron,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 2. is now awakened, and ſits as Judge overall your Actions, accuſing in one thing, excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in another; now if Conſcience he not a Bridle, it will be a Whip, if it be not a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170385:56"/>
Curb, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will be a Scourge, if you will not hear the Warnings you ſhall feel the Laſhes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if it doth not reſtrain from Sin by admonition, it will put u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to pain in ſin by Contrition.</p>
               <p>The Senſes alſo they come to be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Heb. 5. 14. <hi>to diſcern both good and evil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the Senſe of Hearing is frequently exerciſed in hearing the joyfull ſound; and the Senſe of Seeing is exerciſed in beholding the wonderfull works of God; and the Senſe of Smelling is exerciſed, ſmelling a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in Chriſt, and all his wayes; and ſo for the reſt of the Senſes, they are ever now and then exerciſed about ſpiritual things.</p>
               <p>The Vertues of the Soul, or graces of the Spirit, they begin alſo to be employ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d about matters of great concernment, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith endeavours to believe, and lay hold on God for what he hath promiſed; Hope anchors upon the promiſe, and waits with patience for a ſupply of all its wants; Love is exerci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d in loving of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and People, and ſometimes in doing good to his enemies; Prudence i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> whereby we foreſee how things ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in reſpect of time, place, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and what will be the event of each b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs which is undertaken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prudence in our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170385:57"/>
hearts to guide our thoughts, and in our mouths, to order our ſpeeches; it is pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the evils of ſin to chooſe none, and in the evils of puniſhment to chooſe the leſſer, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 12.</p>
               <p>Another Vertue which begins to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, is Temperance, which moderates our deſires, and brings the Appetite under a rule of reaſon; then Conſtancy or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance is another Vertue, whereby a man is reſolved to perſevere to the end in the knowledge, profeſsion, and worſhip of God; Juſtice is another Vertue, which giveth every man his due, it binds us to give due to God, to our Parents, and Kindred, and to exerciſe Verity and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all that we do; lo what a wonderfull change is here! yet notwithſtanding all this, the Soul is the ſame after converſion as it was before, and ſo it ſhall be after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection the ſame: there being the ſame faculties, only thus changed, the Soul, is renewed and reſtored to its primitive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and ſo its purity and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is or ſhall be greater than ever it was before, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus the Regenerate doth partake of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther begetting, of another birth, of another nature, that a man ſhould be the ſame, and not the ſame, the ſame man for Body, yet
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170385:57"/>
as different in quality, as if another ſoul did dwell in the ſame body; he of a lyon, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> become a lamb, of a wolfe, a ſheep, of a <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>Paul,</hi> of a perſecuter, a friend of the perſecuted; here is a bleſſed change indeed, Wouldſt thou know whether thou art rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, art thou one whom God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned? art thou one whom he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath called? art thou one who art waſhed, purged, renewed, ſanctyfied? examine thy heart throughly, deceits lie low, and falſe evidence is the fruit of a ſlight ſearch; Art thou one whoſe heart is taken with Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when God delights in us, thereupon we come to delight in him, God knows us, and thereupon we come to know him, <hi>John.</hi> 10. 14. God apprehends us, and thereupon we come to apprehend him, he chuſeth us, and thereupon we chuſe him, he loves us, and therefore we love him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4. 19. his heart is taken with us, and thereupon we come to be taken with him: take thy evidences from the carriage of thy ſpirit, neither at the beſt, nor at the worſt, but the middle way, which is moſt thy frame; for if thou look upon thy ſelf at the worſt, thou mayſt be diſcouraged, if at the beſt, thou mayſt be deceived, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judg of thy ſelf by particular actions, but look upon the univerſal frame and ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170385:58"/>
of thy ſpirit, art thou heavy laden with the weight of thy offences? doſt thou groan under the yoak and tyrannie of manifold temptations, <hi>Come unto me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I will refreſh the,</hi> Mat. 11. 28. Doeſt thou thirſt after the wayes of grace, <hi>loe I am the living ſpring,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Come drinks, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is my blood that was ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſinnes?</hi> are the wounds of thy tranſgreſſions ſo deep, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>annot be ſearched, or ſo old, that they corrupt and pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie? loe here is the good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> that will either eind them up, or powr in oyle and wine: are there any ſeeds of true life began? is there any motion of repentance in thy ſoul? will thy pulſe of remorſe heat a little? haſt thou but a touch of ſorrow, a ſpark of contrition, a grain of faith, a drop of ſelf denyal? ſurely he that hath began this good work, will finiſh it? <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 6. Surely he will more and more inform thy mind, conform thy will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thy life, and tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>form the whole man into the likeneſs of the heavenly pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, a man that is born again may be weak in reſpect of life, in whom the ſpirit breath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> though feintly, whoſe pulſe beats but feebly, whoſe heart pants after Chriſt but weakly, in whom Chriſt, who is the wiſdome of the father, ſhines, though
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170385:58"/>
through many clouds very dimly, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ives Chriſt and his free g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, though with a ſhaking hand, who hopes that Chriſt will not caſt him off, though not ſure he will take him up, he hath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to fear the name of the Lord: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath <hi>a willing mind,</hi> 2 Cor. 8. 12, and this is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable with the Lord, a <hi>will</hi> to obey the Lord, is all that a bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> can ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times find, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 18. One may be a babe in Chriſt though carnal. 1 Cor. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>and I brethren could not ſpeak unto you as unto ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as unto carnal, even as unto babes in Chriſt;</hi> or as ſome rendreth the word, <hi>as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſucklings in Chriſt.</hi> To cloſeup this, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, one drop of water is for the quality, the ſame as the whole Ocean Sea, one grain of gold, is as pure gold as a whole moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of gold, the leaſt bud by the ſide of a great tree, draws ſap from the ſame root that the greateſt limb or branch doth; So the leaſt meaſure of grace, is as true grace, as the greateſt meaſure; it is as pure for the quality, though not ſo much for the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity. Our ſalvation depends upon the truth of grace, our conſolation depends upon the degree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170385:59"/>
               <head>Certain Objections anſwered, which ſome out of weakneſs, and others out of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, may be apt to make againſt the foregoing Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. If a people refuſe to imbrace the doctrine, and practice the diſciplin of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whether they are not to be forced to receive the one, and practiſe the other, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ:</hi> Religion is to be taught, not to be forced, and that for theſe reaſons;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe Chriſt and his Apoſtles never uſed any force in propagating of religion; not the ſword, but the Word and Prayer, were the inſtruments uſed to propagate chriſtianity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be not in our own power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, till it be given us from above, how can it be in the power of any other to make us believe? how can they forceus to take that which is not given, and to profeſs that which we have not received?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Religion is the free gift of God, which as it is freely given, ſo it muſt be freely received, without conſtraint; for the will cannot be forced.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As he is not to be eſteemed an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, or an Idolater, that is forced thereto, neither is he to be eſteemed religious that is compelled to embrace it.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170385:59"/>5ly. The forcing of Religion hath been the cauſe of much miſchief, <hi>viz.</hi> murthers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſorders and changes in States; <q>Therfore the wiſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Woll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bius,</hi> p. 332 permitted the <hi>Iews,</hi> after they were ſubdued, to uſe freely their own Religion:</q> But men are to be warned, and exhorted to make uſe of the means. If the acts of hearing, reading, praying, meditation, conference, are means by which Religion is both begot and nouriſhed, to neglect the uſe of theſe and the like means, is to neglect our own ſalvation, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Whether liberty of conſcience be, as ſome ſay, a curſed toleration, or of divine institution, yea, or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> If under a pretence of liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, men ſhall own any other God, or preach any other Chriſt, or Goſpel, than what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, or preſs people to walk by any other rule, this undoubtedly is a curſed tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation, and to be lamented. But for a people that doth hold the head, and agree in the doctrinal part of Religion holding all to the eſſence of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial truths, if they differ ſomwhat in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, how, and when, and in what plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s this God is to be worſhipped; here in the ſtrong muſt bear with the weak, and give the new-born babes leave to feed upon milk, and the child to ſpeak and think as a child, whilſt the young man is grabling with gainſayers, and the old man going on to perfection; and thus, ſeeing the one cannot ſee by the others eyes, Col. 2. 6. <hi>As ye have therefore received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him; Nevertheleſs, whereunto ye
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170385:60"/>
have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame things,</hi> Phil. 3. 15. 16. <hi>If in any thing ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal even this unto you.</hi> Vniformity in diſcipline, as well as in doctrine, is much to be deſired, and the want of it to be lamented, and the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of it to be indeavoured, by all that are truly convicted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Qu. <hi>What is, or ought to be the ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manion and fellowſhip in the church of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Vnion: For without union there is no communion or fellowſhip; a Chriſtian having Chriſt formed in him, comes by degrees to ſee his union with him, and from that union with Chriſt, as the ground and foundation, deſires to joyn himſelf in fellowſhip with the people of Chriſt, that he may inquire in his temple, and behold his glory, and injoy the communion of Saints, which is a great part of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> comfort on earth: See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. compared with 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Whether there be any preparatory work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of men and women before converſion: and if ſo, what it is?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An:</hi> According to the ordinary diſpenſation of God, the ſoul is made ſenſible of ſin, and the wages thereof death, curſe and hell, but all the preparatory works before converſion, may be reduced to theſe few heads.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Revelation of its finful and loſt eſtate, ſo far as to acknowledge himſelf a lawfull captive.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Revelation of Chriſt in ſome ſmall meaſure, in and by whom there is a poſſibility of obtein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The ſoul is reſolved to wait on God in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170385:60"/>
uſe of means, for the obtaining of mercy.</p>
                  <p>But let the Reader take notice, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preparations and qualifications there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, they are firſt wrought in us by the finger of God, who worketh in us both to will and to doe of his own good pleaſure: man is merely paſſive in the firſt work of converſion or rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, he could not ſo much as really wiſh it; but in all the reſt man is a fellow-worker with God, he is the inſtrument, though not the cauſe of his own ſalvation: <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord ſpeaks, and he hears, the Lord calls, and he anſwereth the Lord draws, and he comes, the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and he in ſome meaſure obeyeth; man is not like a ſtock when he is called, for he is the fit ſubject of vocation, ſeeing he is a reaſonable creature, yet his reaſon helps him nothing to his vocation, till it be enlightned, and ſo the minde is changed, and the ſtonie heart ſoftned, <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>Whether there be not a free-will remaining in all the posterity of Adam?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> A mans will remains free, but it is to evil only, <hi>the imagination of the heart is only evil,</hi> Gen. 6. 5 Mans will is not free, until it be by grace made free: yet poor man would be like the Spider, ſpinning out a thred of his own, and ſo think to climb up to heaven by a thred ſpun out of his own bowels; wheras we are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of our ſelves to think that is good as of our ſelves, but all our ſufficiency is of God 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 5.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>Whether Adam by his fall did totally loſe eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y good thing that there was in him, yea, or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An:</hi> By original ſin our natural gifts are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, but ſupernatural gifts are utterly loſt; but
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170385:61"/>
he and all his poſterity retain ſome footſteps and impreſſions, though not of grace, yet of gifts, he did not utterly loſe the knowledge of God, nor did his poſterity, for that is learned by the things that are made, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20. Nor did he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſe the fear of God, for <hi>Adam</hi> confeſſed, <hi>Gen:</hi> 3. that when he heard the voice of God, he was afraid: there remains ſome ſcraps of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by which he acts prudently, as to worldly affairs, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 8. Again, he walks toward his fellow-creatures in the performance of certain acts of duty and charity, as they ſtand related to him, and his light or conſcience, excuſing or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, according to his acting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>How came the ſin of Adam, being but one man, to be made the ſin of ſo many men, yea of all, ſeeing they eat not the apple?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An:</hi> The ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> in eating the forbidden fruit, is made ours by participation and imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By participation: <hi>Adam</hi> being a publick perſon, all his poſterity was conteined in his loins, and ſo ſinned in his ſinning, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 12.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By imputation: the Lord doth impute the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal guilt therof unto his whole poſterity deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from him by way of ordinary generation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18 19. compared with-1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>How could Chriſt, being but one, make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for the ſins of ſo many?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An:</hi> How could <hi>Adam</hi> being but one inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct ſo many with original ſin? the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was as publike a perſon as the firſt, and as well able to ſanctifie, as the firſt to putrifie: and farther, though Chriſt was but one, yet he was ſuch a
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170385:61"/>
one as was greater and better than all, and ſo able and ſufficient to ſatisfie for all, and to redeem all, for the blood of ſuch an one as Chriſt the ſon of God, was of ſuch an infinite value and price, that it did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urmount and ſurpaſs in dignity and worth all the ſouls of the world, and his ſufferings and merits were a ſufficient ſatisfaction, if intended and to that end, for to ſave ſo many worlds of men as there is men in the world; for all things beſides God came from nothing, and are in themſelves nothing: It is true, God calleth himſelf I <hi>am, Exod.</hi> 3. 14. We are but created reſults of God, bits of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancies upon him, we are of yeſterday, little branches budding from our mother nothing, by the alone will and pleaſure of God, <hi>Iſa. 40. 15. 17. Behold all nations are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him as a drop of a bucket, as the ſmall duſt of the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, as a very little thing, as nothing, as leſs than nothing, even as vanity, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>What are we to underſtand by Election and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which are mentioned in the Scriptures, and ſo many people contending about?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Gods eternal purpoſe according to the counſel of his will, for his own glory he hath fore-ordeined what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever comes to paſs, voluntarily to ſave ſome through Chriſt: but others being left to themſelves in their own fin and miſery to periſh eternally; and albeit God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moſt freely, and according to his good pleaſure, yet neither have the Elect any juſt cauſe to boaſt, nor the Reprobate to complain: for to the one undeſerved grace was beſtowed, and on the other deſerved puniſhment is inflicted. Again, conſider, that as predeſtination is a part of Gods providence: ſo is Reprobation; for as God by his providence hath ordeined ſome to life eternal, ſo by that ſame providence, he was pleaſed to ſuffer ſome to fall away from that happineſs: they are altogether fooliſh,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170385:62"/>
who acknowledge election, and deny reprobation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eacheth, that there is a reprobation as well as election, Iſa. 41. 9. <hi>I have choſen thee, and not caſt thee away,</hi> Mal. 1. 3. <hi>Jacob have I loved, and I have hated Eſau,</hi> Rom. 9. 18. <hi>He will have mercie on whom he will, and whom he will be hardneth,</hi> Rom. 11. 7. <hi>The electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath obtained it, and the rest have been hardned,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 9. <hi>God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to ſalvation,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 20. <hi>Veſſels to honour, and to diſhonour,</hi> Jude verſ. 4. <hi>For there are certain men crept in which were before of old ordained to condemnation.</hi> So that we may learn from theſe Scriptures, that if Chriſt ſheweth a people mercy, it is fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and meer mercy, if he doth not ſhew them mercy he doth them no wrong, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 15, 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>Then Election ſeemeth to be the cauſe of ſalvation, and Reprobation the cauſe of damnation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Election and Reprobation are not in any ſenſe the cauſes of ſalvation and damnation, but Chriſt is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and meritorious cauſe of ſalvation, and Sin the proper and meritorious cauſe of damnation; election and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, they are but precedent acts or decrees, and the cauſes of ſalvation and damnation; they come in between the decrees and the execution thereof. If it be demanded, Why the Potter out of the ſame lump makes veſſels of ſuch different condition? It is anſwered, becauſe there be different uſes of thoſe veſſels in the houſe. If again it be demanded, Why out of one piece of the ſame lump a veſſel of honour is made, and a veſſel to diſhonour? It is anſwered becauſe itſo pleaſed the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. O the unlimited Soveraignty of the being of beings. how unſearchable are his judgements and his wayes paſt finding out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 33.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>Whether Chriſt hath dyed for all men, and taſted death for every man,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 15. 1 Tim. 2. 6. as theſe Scriptures ſeem to affirm?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170385:62"/>
                     <hi>An:</hi> The word <hi>all</hi> hath many reſtrictions in Scripture, and ſo hath the word <hi>every man;</hi> as to inſtance, the word <hi>all</hi> is ſometimes reſtrained in Scripture to the Lords pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people, <hi>John 12. 32. Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will drsw all men to him,</hi> that is, all men that the father gave him: <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. 45. Again, we read <hi>They ſhall be all taught of God,</hi> not all the world ſure, but all Gods people. Again, <hi>Acts 2. 7. I will powr out my Spirit upon all fleſh,</hi> this place cannot be meant of all the wicked. Again we read, 1 <hi>Theſſ. 2. 15. They pleaſe not God, and are contrary to all men,</hi> that is, all good men. Again we read, <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake,</hi> that is, of all wicked men: So we ſee the word <hi>all</hi> is taken variouſly: and when as it is ſaid he <hi>tasted death for every man,</hi> it is to be taken for ſome of all kinreds, tongues and people. As to inſtance, <hi>Cant. 3. 8. Every man had his ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd on his thigh:</hi> So Micah 4. 4. <hi>Every man ſhall ſit under his vine:</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 4. 5. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall have praiſe of God.</hi> Now let us conſider, every mon in the world had not a ſword to wear, nor a vine to ſit under, neither ſhall every man have praiſe of God: much more might be ſaid to this, but this point is fully deba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, and anſwered by many precious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whoſe books are extant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>How can they have hope to believe, whom God hath decreed ſhall not believe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> We are according to ordinary diſpenſation to look at all living under the goſpel, to be capable of believing, and in the judgement of charity, for ought we know, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; and it is the duty of every one, to whom the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of faith is propounded, to believe: and it is the duty of every believer, to believe, that he is elected. Again, God together with the object of faith, tenders us means, ſo farr ſufficient to the begetting of faith, as leaveth us without excuſe; we love our unbelief, and reſiſt this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170385:63"/>
means of believing, John 1. 11. <hi>He came to his own and they received him not.</hi> John 5. 40. <hi>And you will not come to me that ye might have life.</hi> If we look on God with a legal eye, ſo the leaſt ſinner is uncapable; but if wee look at him with an evangelical eye, ſo the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is capable of mercy. <hi>Abraham</hi> becometh a father, and <hi>Sarah</hi> a mother, by overcoming ſuch temptations as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe from his dead body, and the deadneſs of her womb. Again, let us conſider, though the decree be abſolute, yet the diſpenſation of the decree in the goſpel is condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, <hi>Whoſoever believeth ſhall be ſaved,</hi> John 3. 16. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 20. Again, who dare ſay that God hath decreed that he ſhould not believe? This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree is a ſecret thing, and ſecret things belong to God, and revealed things to us: a man may know he is elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when he hath made his calling and election ſure; but no man can ſay he is reprobated, till he is given up to a reprobate ſenſe. We read in many places of Scripture, that it is the duty of every one to believe, and we finde in many other places of Scripture, that God is the author of faith, which is wrought in our hearts by his mighty power, ſo that without him we cannot believe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q. Now, why doth the moſt juſt and righteous God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all to believe, and promiſe ſalvation to them that doe believe, and threaten damnation to all that doe not believe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeing it is not in mans power to believe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Anſ</hi> For theſe Five Reaſons:</head>
                     <item>1. That he might by means of thoſe promiſes and threats, work us unto that which by nature we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe unto, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 11. 20. Knowing therefore the terror of the Lord, we perſwade men, we are ambaſſadors for Christ as though God did beſeech you by us, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That the ſons and daughters of men might appear m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re inexcuſab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, when neither promiſes nor threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170385:63"/>
will move them to imbrace free mercy, <hi>Acts</hi> 13 46. 51. and <hi>Acts</hi> 18. 6.</item>
                     <item>3. That the grace of God might as well appear in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us power to believe, as in giving Chriſt, and in him forgiveneſs of ſins to be believed, <hi>Rom. 9. 16. Rom.</hi> 11. 5. 6.</item>
                     <item>4. That we might apply ourſelves unto God, in the uſe of means appointed by him for the working of faith in us, <hi>Iſa. 55. 3. John</hi> 6. 27.</item>
                     <item>5. That we might ſearch, and by ſearching find in the covenant of grace, matter of free conveyance of power to believe whatſoever is required to be believed, <hi>Rom. 10. 17. John. 5. 39<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rom.</hi> 4. 16.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Qu. <hi>Whether there: be not a light in every man, which if improved and walkt up to, would lead us to the gate of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if not into heaven, yea or no?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> God doth give to every man ſome talent or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, which if people did improve, ſhould be increaſed, and the party much advantaged, &amp;c. the ſame Lord doth give to ſome natural talents, as wiſdom, wealth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, &amp;c. and to others ſpiritual talents or gifts, as to pray, propheſie, in erpret, &amp;c. and God may juſtly condemn men for not improving what he gives them, we read that the heathen that had but the very light of nature, <hi>Rom</hi> 1. and 2. chapters, their walking not up to that, left them without excuſe: but withall conſider, that not to minde the light within him, ſo as to improve that and all other talents given him, is enough to damn him, yet the improvement thereof is not ſufficient to ſave him: the Law that every man hath broken, muſt have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, perſonal, perpetual, univerſal obedience, or elſe it leaves us under the curſe, and all our improvements can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not purchaſe the pardon of one ſin; If the ſtung <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> had made a medicin of the beſt herbs in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a plaiſter of all the ſoverein ingredients in the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170385:64"/>
whole world, and applied it with mountains of prayers, and ſeas of tears, yet this would not have helped them, if withall they did not look upon the brazen ſerpent, and all becauſe that was Gods way of healing, &amp;c. So now Gods way of ſaving, is not by or for the improvement of light, but by the obedience of Chriſt for us, and his righteouſneſs imputed to us: and therefore in Scripture we read, that our ſalvation is attributed all to grace, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 3. 7 Rom. 3. 24. Rom. 4. 5. Iſa.</hi> 43. 23, 24, 25. All our beſt and choiceſt performances are but gilded ſins, we can doe nothing which is truly, really and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially good, no not ſo much as think a good thought, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5. Neither are we able to underſtand as we ought, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. Neither able to will any thing that is good, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 13. Neither able to begin a good work, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 6. Neither able to perfect it when it is begun, <hi>Iſa. 26. 12. Rom.</hi> 7. 18. So that in all our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements there is ſtill imperfection, ſomething pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo that our moſt Spiritual duties are not wound up to command they are all tainted with diſproportion to rule, and be-leopard with ſpots, ſo that it is in vain to expect a bed, or reſt in the bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en wilderneſs of our own performances, <hi>Iſa. 28. 20. This bed is ſhorter than that a man can stretch himſelf on it, and the covering is narrower than that a man can wrap himſelf in it.</hi> Iſa. 50. 11. <hi>Behold all ye that kindle a fire, walk in the light of your fire, and in the spark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that ye have kindled, this ſhall ye have of my hand, ye ſhall lie down in ſorrow;</hi> Our own righteouſnes is called a monſtrous rag; a rag, &amp; therfore cannot cover us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> monſtrous, and therefore if it ſhould cover us, it would but cover filth with filth: <hi>Iſa. 30. 1. They cover, but not with the covering of my spirit, that they might add ſin to ſin:</hi> that is, the ſin of their own righteouſneſs, to the ſin of their unrighteouſneſs, they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170385:64"/>
a blot with a blot, add ſin to ſin, dung to dung.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q <hi>But how doth it more particularly appear that our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, ſalvation, and glorification, &amp;c. is purely, clearly and only of grace, and nothing but grace?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Election is the election of grace, and <hi>according to the good pleaſure of his will,</hi> Eph. 1. 5.</p>
                  <p>Vocation is alſo of grace, 2 Tim. 1. 9. <hi>Who hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us in Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Regeneration is of Gods own will, <hi>James 1. 18. Of his own will begat he us by the word of truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Faith is alſo <hi>the free gift of God,</hi> Philip. 1. 29.</p>
                  <p>Juſtification is <hi>freely by grace,</hi> Rom. 3. 24.</p>
                  <p>Forgiveneſs of ſinnes is according to the riches of his grace, Eph: 1. 7. <hi>In whom we have redemption through his bloud, the forgiveneſs of our ſins, according to the riches of his grace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eternal life alſo <hi>is the gift of God,</hi> Rom. 6. 23.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Qu <hi>If theſe and the like precious things be only of grace, without works, then in what respect are good works neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An.</hi> Good works are neceſſary,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. in reſpect of God.</item>
                     <item>2. in reſpect of our ſelves.</item>
                     <item>3. in reſpect of others.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>1. Works are good in reſpect of God.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. to ſhew our obedience.</item>
                     <item>2. to glorifie his name.</item>
                     <item>3. to teſtifie our thankfulneſs.</item>
                     <item>4. to beautifie his goſpel.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſhew our obedience: Rom. 6. 16. <hi>To whom ye yield your ſelves ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are to whom ye obey, whether of ſin unto death, or of obedience
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170385:65"/>
unto righteouſneſs.</hi> See <hi>John</hi> 8. 34. compared with 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To glorifie his name, Mat. 5. 16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 12. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your converſation honeſt among the gentils, that when as they speak againſt you as evil doers, they may by your good works, which they ſhall behold, glorifie God in the day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</hi> See Theſſ. 1. 12.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To teſtifie our thankfulneſs, when we conſider, that we our ſelves, together with the reſidue of mankind, lay equally in the guilt and pollution of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin: he free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave unto us ſo excellent a being after his own Image, leaving our fellow ſinners unto miſery, from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he appointed his ſon to deſcend as low as hell to fetch us from thence, and to aſcend up as high as heaven to carry us up thither: this is the great and glorious cauſe of thankſgiving, ſaying in theſe or the like words, Pſal. 116. 12. <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits towards me?</hi> Whatſoever we are, we are by him, whatſoever we have, we have received from him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we are or have, we owe to him, <hi>Rom. 11. 36. Of him and through him are all things, to whom be glory for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Good works are neceſſary to beautifie the Goſpel, Philip. 1. 27. <hi>Let your converſation be as it becometh the Gospel of Chriſt.</hi> And in the 2 Col. 9. 13. there were a people commended fortheir <hi>profeſſed ſibjection to the gospel:</hi> ſurely unleſs we maintain and keep up good works in our converſation, we walk unworthy of God, <hi>Col. 1 10. That ye might walk worthy of the Lord, unto all pleaſing, being fruit failin every good work, &amp;c.</hi> Nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if we are negligent in obeying, we walk unworthy of our calling, Eph. 4. 1. <hi>I beſeech you, that ye walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170385:65"/>
of the vocation wherewith ye are called,</hi> Tit. 2. 10. that we might adorn the doctrin of God out Saviour in all things; for indeed an holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is the end of our election, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1, 4. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>John</hi> 15. 16. Again, it is the end of our redemption, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. compared with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15. Nay farther, it is the end of our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15. compared with 1 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 4. 7. Laſtly, a holy converſation is the end of our new creation, Eph. 2. 10. <hi>We are created in christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus unto good works, which God hath ordained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> So much for the firſt of theſe. Good works are neceſſary in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, to ſhew our obedience, to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his name, to teſtifie our thankfulneſs, and to beautifie his goſpel, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>2. Good works are neceſſary in reſpect of our ſelves,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As it is the way of conveyance of mercy to us.</item>
                     <item>2. To declare and manifeſt our ſincerity.</item>
                     <item>3. This is the way to have a being, and a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being.</item>
                     <item>4. This is the way to make our calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. They are neceſſary in reſpect of our ſelves, as they are the pipes of conveyance of both the apprehenſion and application of mercy to us: See theſe Scriptures, <hi>Pſal. 50. 23. To him that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth his converſation aright, will I ſhew the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God.</hi> Pſal. 107. 43. <hi>Who ſo is wiſe and will obſerve theſe things, even they ſhall understand the loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi> John 14, 21. <hi>He that hath my commandements, and keepeth them,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170385:66"/>
he it is that loveth me, and he that loveth me ſhall be loved of my father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf to him.</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 12. <hi>For this is our rejoycing, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, we have had our converſation among you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. They are neceſſary to clear and manifeſt our ſincerity, both to ourſelves and others; to our ſelves, as they ſpring from a right principle, and are regulated by a pure rule, and done to a good end, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5. compared with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31,  to others, they know a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee by its fruits, they know where faith is by its works, and where love is by its effects, 1 John. 1. 6. <hi>If we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him and walk in darkneſs, we lye and do not the truth,</hi> ſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 7. 8.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They are neceſſary as to our being and well being, Pſal. 37. 3. <hi>Truſt in the Lord and do good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi> Mat. 16. 27. <hi>He will reward every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. This is the way to make our calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>For if ye do theſe things, ye ſhall never fall, for ſo an entrance ſhall be administred unto you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the everlaſting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. Good works are neceſſary in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 8. they that have believed in Chriſt, muſt be carefull to doe good works, for theſe things are good and profitable to men, in theſe four-ſold reſpects,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To ſtop the mouths of wicked men.</item>
                     <item>2. To increaſe the joy of the Lords people.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170385:66"/>3. To win others to the embracing of the Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>4. For an example of vertue.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſtop the mouthes of wicked men, who will condemn ſin in a Profeſſor, although they will approve of it in themſelves, 1 <hi>Pet. 217. For ſo is the will of God, that with well-doing we may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men:</hi> this made wicked <hi>Saul</hi> ſay to <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 24. 17. <hi>Thou art more righteous than I, for thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded me good for evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. To increaſe the joy of the Lords people, Col. 2. 5. <hi>for though I am abſent in the fleſh, yet am I with you in the ſpirit, joying and beholding your order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of your faith in Chriſt.</hi> So again the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>I rejoyced greatly,</hi> ſaith John, <hi>that I found of thy children walking in truth.</hi> Surely it is a great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to one Chriſtian to ſee the forwardneſs of another in the waies of well doing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To win others to the imbracing of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol, 1 Pet. 3. 1, 2. that they may be won by the converſation, <hi>whilst they behold your chaſte converſation coupled with fear, &amp;c.</hi> A man doth teach by his converſation, as well as by his doctrine.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Good works and an holy converſation are good in reſpect of others, for an example of Vertue, Joh. 13. 15. <hi>I have done this good work to give you an example,</hi> ſaid our Lord Chriſt; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain we read, Theſ. 1. 7. <hi>So that ye were examples to all that believe:</hi> And indeed each Officer in the Church ſhould walk ſo, as to be a good example to the Flock; there is ateaching by
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170385:67"/>
Example as well as by Doctrine. See <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 17. By all which we may ſee that good works are neceſſary, in reſpect of the Lord which doth command them, and of our ſelves that doth them, and of others that behold them: although there is no man ſaved for his good works, yet there is none ſaved without them. Many other Arguments might begiven to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to be rich in good works: to inſtance in few, and ſo to cloſe this Anſwer to this Queſtion, conſider then, (1.) That all the commands of God to walk holy, are but as ſo many perſwaſions to perſwade us to be happy, Deut. 5. 29. <hi>That it might go well with us and our Children.</hi> (2.) Becauſe Chriſtians <hi>are the ſalt of the Earth, the light of the world, a City ſet upon a Hill that cannot be hid,</hi> Mat. 5. 13, 14. (3.) <hi>Seeing that death and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the end of this life and world is at hand,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 11, &amp;c. (4.) <hi>There is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to thoſe that walk not after the fleſh but after the spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. 1. (5.) <hi>This is the way to have Gods bleſsing upon all we ſet our hand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> Pſal. 1. 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> You have here preſented us with our Duty and the benefits and privileges that will redound to us if we obey, but how ſhall we be enabled to do theſe things? Jer. 10. 23. <hi>the way of man is not in himſelf, it is not in man that walketh to direct his steps;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us from the Lord, <hi>that we are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as of our ſelves to think ſo much as one good thought, and that it is God that worketh both to will and to do, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170385:67"/>Anſw. <hi>Strength to perform any duty to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any Grace, to ſubdue any Lust, or reſiſt any Temptation, to bear any Affliction, &amp;c. is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only from the Lord, one of theſe three wayes to the Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider, That either he hath already before hand, as it were, enabled us to do the thing commanded, by giving us a Talent, or Talents, 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 8, 9, 10. Rom. 12. 6, Mat.</hi> 25. 15. to 28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let us conſider, That many times the Lord conveys a power together with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to enable us to do the thing commanded: So when he bid <hi>Lazarus</hi> come forth of the Grave: ſo when he commanded the man that was ſick of the palſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to take up his Bed and walk, <hi>Lu.</hi> 5. 24, 25. So again, <hi>Ezek. 2. 1, 2. And he ſaid unto me, Son of Man ſtand upon thy feet, and I will speak unto thee, and the spirit en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into me when he spake, and ſet me upon my feet, and I heard him speak unto me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If we find no power already given us before the command, neither any power conveyed to us, together with the command; then in the next place, we are to bring the command to the Promiſe, and ſo to ſeek (for) by Prayer, the bleſsing of the Promiſe, that we may be enabled to do the Duty of the Precept. <hi>To</hi> inſtance in a few caſes for all the reſt,</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to believe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. 15.<note place="margin">Precept. Promiſe. Prayer.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Believing is Gods free gift, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
                  <p>This puts the Soul upon praying for it, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, help my unbelief, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 24.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to waſh and be clean, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Precept.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170385:68"/>It is Gods promiſe to ſanctifie and cleanſe<note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25.</p>
                  <p>The Soul ſeeing its duty, and Gods promiſe,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> prayes, Waſh me, and I ſhall be clean, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 2.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 30.<note place="margin">Precept. Promiſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The promiſe holds forth repentance, as the gift of God, <hi>Acts 5. 31. 2 Tim.</hi> 2. 25.</p>
                  <p>Prayer ſues it out, Turn thou me and I ſhall<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> be turned, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 18.</p>
                  <p>It is required of man as his duty to make him<note place="margin">Precept.</note> anew heart, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 31.</p>
                  <p>It is Gods promiſe to give a new heart. <hi>Ezec.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> 36 26.</p>
                  <p>Create in me a new heart O God, and renew<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> a right Spirit within me, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. 10.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to love God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 37.<note place="margin">Precept. Promiſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is Gods promiſe to circumciſe the heart to love him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6.</p>
                  <p>The Lord direct your hearts into the love<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> of God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to fear God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 12.<note place="margin">Precept. Promiſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is Gods promiſe to put his fear into our<note place="margin">Precept. Promiſe.</note> hearts, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32. 40.</p>
                  <p>Prayer ſeeks for it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 11. Unite my<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> heart to fear thy name.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to draw near to God, <hi>Iawes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Precept.</note> 4. 8.</p>
                  <p>It is Chriſts promiſe to draw men unto him,<note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. 32.</p>
                  <p>Prayer falls in ſutable herunto, <hi>Can.</hi> 1. 4. Draw<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> me, we will run after thee.</p>
                  <p>It is mans dutie to walk in Gods Statutes,<note place="margin">Precept.</note> 
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 4,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170385:68"/>It is Gods promiſe to inable men ſo to do,<note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 27.</p>
                  <p>O that my ways were directed to keep thy<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> ſtatutes, <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 119. 5.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to be ſtrong in the Lord,<note place="margin">Precept.</note> 
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 10.</p>
                  <p>It is Gods promiſe to make him ſtrong, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> 29. 11.</p>
                  <p>Prayer falls in, O give thy ſtrength to thy<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> Servant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 16.</p>
                  <p>It is mans duty to draw near to, but not to<note place="margin">Precept.</note> depart from God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.</p>
                  <p>It is Gods promiſe to his people that they<note place="margin">Promiſe.</note> ſhall not depart from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32 40.</p>
                  <p>O let me not wander from thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> 
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 10.</p>
                  <p>Let the Reader conſider, that to each pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there is a promiſe, and to ſome precepts there are two or three promiſes: the one to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us the other to reward us, and all to encourage us to do our duty: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands in Scripture doth not ſo much ſhew what the Creature can do, but what he ſhould do, yet not by his own natural power, but by his aſſiſting and enabling grace. In a word, Duty is the matter of Gods Promiſe, as well as Gods Mercy, as doth moſt clearly appear by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Epheſ. 2. 8. Phil. 1. 29. Acts 5. 31. John</hi> 8. 32.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the best way to mortifie ſin that is ſo prevailing in us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The beſt way to mortifie our fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts, is, to meditate on the mercies of God, which is one of the moſt powerfull Arguments to perſwade and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170385:69"/>
prevail with a Soul to leave ſin, Pſal. 26. 3, 4. <hi>For thy loving kindneſſe is before mine eyes, and I have walked in thy truth,</hi> 1 John 3. 3. <hi>he that hath this hope in him purifieth himſelf, as he is pure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> I have read of five men that were ſtudying, what was the beſt way to mortifie ſin; The firſt ſaid, to meditate of death: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſaid, to meditate of judgement to come: the third ſaid, to meditate on the joys of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: the fourth ſaid, to meditate on the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell, which is the wages of ſin: the fifth ſaid, to meditate on the blood and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Ieſus Chriſt. And certainly the laſt is the ſtrongeſt motive of all to mortifie ſin: ſurely it is the appearance of Gods grace to us, which works a hope of glory in us, and this hope of glory doth purifie, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 3. both in kind and degree, 2 <hi>Cor. 7. 1. Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe, both of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> Rom. 8. 13. And ſo by the Spirit we come to mortifie the deeds of the fleſh; he that hath the ſtrongeſt Faith hath the holyeſt life, Sanctification a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from Juſtification; let us then make war againſt our Luſts in the ſtrength of Chriſt, ſtill ſeeking unto him for aſſiſting grace; for as we have ſaid before in this Treatiſe, ſtrength to perform any duty, to exerciſe any grace, to ſubdue any Luſt, to reſiſt any temptation, to bear any affliction, is derived only from Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Queſt <hi>What is, or who is the object of Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God the Father Son, &amp; holy Ghoſt, is the object of ſaving Faith, no man was ever ſaved without this, for no man ever called upon God, but by the help of the holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 3. As no man can ſay, that Jeſus is the Chriſt, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170385:69"/>
can any man ſay that God is God, but by the holy Ghoſt:</hi> neither did God ever hear any man that prayed unto him for ſalvation, but for his Sons ſake: we are in order, not in time, to believe, firſt in Chriſt, &amp; by Chriſt in God, 1 <hi>pet. 1. 21. Who by him do believe in God.</hi> We are commanded to believe in Chriſt, 1 Joh, 3. 23. <hi>and this is his commandement, that we ſhould believe in the name of his Son Jeſus Christ;</hi> for Chriſt as Redeemer is the mediate, not the ultimate object of Faith, for we believe by Chriſt in God, as before;</p>
                  <p>As Chriſt is the object of divine worſhip, <hi>Asts</hi> 7. 59.</p>
                  <p>And of ſaving hope, <hi>Collo.</hi> 1. 27.</p>
                  <p>And of our greateſt love, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22.</p>
                  <p>And of our abſolute ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 9. 18.</p>
                  <p>So he is the object of our divine Faith, together with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt; ſo <hi>John</hi> 14. 1. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21. as God in Trinity is the object of Faith, ſo the Scripture ſeems to be the ground of Faith; Firſt, the Lord preſents us with a command to believe, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 23. and a promiſe of Salvation to them that believe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. 16. and it is the duty of all that do hear the Goſpel to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>Mar. 1. 15. Iohn 3. 18. Iohn 15. 22. &amp;</hi> 16. 7.</p>
                  <p>In the begetting or breeding of Faith in the heart, is manifeſted both the inability of Man and the ability of God: here appears the evil of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of corrupt nature, and the good of the Spirit of Grace; <hi>Sarah</hi> her conceiving of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> whoſe birth was a figure of Regeneration, was a great work, a miracle; ſo <hi>Mary</hi> her conception of Chriſt, by the power, command, and bleſsing of the holy Ghoſt, was alſo a great work, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, but for, Chriſt to be formed in the Soul by
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170385:70"/>
believing, is as great, if not a greater work, ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 19, 20.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>What incouragement and grounds are there to provoke or perſwade us to believe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are many, I will inſtance only in a few<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which may be reduced to theſe two heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The benefits in doing it.</item>
                     <item>2. The hurt or danger in neglecting it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>1. The benefits that doe attend thoſe that doe believe, and they are theſe;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By believing, we honour God our Creator, Chriſt our Redeemer, and the holy Ghoſt our Sanctifier, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 33<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 34.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By believing we come to be eſtabliſhed, <hi>Iſay</hi> 7. 9.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> believing we ſhall be kept in perfect peace, <hi>Iſay</hi> 26. 34. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whoſoever believeth in him ſhall not be aſhamed, <hi>Rom:</hi> 9. 33.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Our naked believing in God, and cleaving to him in his free promiſes, will carry down all our diſtempers at once, and fill our Souls with joy and peace in believing.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This is the way to have God take pleaſure in us, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 147. 11. the Lord taketh pleaſure in thoſe that hope in his mercy, <hi>Pſalm 33. 18. the eyes of the Lord is upon them that fear him, upon them that hope in his mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Our believing doth inſtate the Soul in the poſſeſſion of Heaven, whiles the body remains on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arth. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 36.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. For our incouragement to believe, conſider, Chriſt outbids all Merchants for thy Soul, he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the World, Sin and Sathan; they do not preſent pardon, remiſſion, redemption, ſalvation,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170385:70"/>
but Chriſt doth preſent theſe, and many more ſuch like choyſe things.</p>
                  <p>2. Let us conſider the evil of Unbelief, and the miſery that doth attend it, it is a diſhonouring of God, a denying of Chriſt, it (as much as in it lyeth) makes void the great Counſel of God, and purpoſes of his mercy, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. We do what lyes in us make void Gods end in ſending Chriſt: his end was, that we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and live for ever in bleſſedneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We, as much as in us lyes, make void the death of Chriſt, all his ſufferings and bloodſhed to be to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We make void, what lyes in us, the great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God, and all the thoughts of his wiſedom, in contriving ſuch a way to advance his glory in the ſalvation of man.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By continuing in a ſtate of Unbelief, we rob Chriſt of the reward and fruit of all his ſufferings and death.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. We wrong God by our Unbelief, we obſcure his glory, we limit his power, we contemn his wiſedom, we give a lye to his truth, we abuſe his love, we ſlight and reject all the Precious thoughts of his mercy and grace, we proclaim the Devil a Conquerour, and lift him up above Chriſt himſelf; <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as</hi> did ſin more by Unbelief and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing, than by his betraying of Chriſt, as might be gathered from Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. We haſten damnation to our ſelves, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 18, 36<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Were we in <hi>Adams</hi> created innocency, then we need not to look after a Saviour, but we are all fallen, but we are broken, but we are ſold under ſin, but we are tranſgreſſors from the wombe, but we are by nature the children of diſobedience and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170385:71"/>
wrath. What ſhall I ſay more? Unbelief is the greateſt ſin in the world, becauſe it is a ſin againſt the greateſt love, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 8. it is a ſin againſt the only remedy; the ſentence of the Law may be repealed by the Goſpel, but the ſin againſt Goſpel remedy, there is no repeal of; it is a ſin that makes void and vain all the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, turning all the ſweetneſſe thereof into bitterneſſe, and all the truth of it into a lye, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 10. Therefore God is more ſevere againſt Unbelief than any ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Unbelief is moſt ſevereto God, God hath no greater Enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in the world than Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Let us conſider, that a man without Faith is like a naked man in a ſtorm, or like an una<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>med man in a Battel, like a ſhip unanchored, and unballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in a ſtorm, he is like a Sea without Banks, a world without a Sun, or a ſhip without a Pilot, he is under the command of all his paſſions and enemies, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Qu. <hi>In what way are we to conceive of God when we pray to him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are not to conceive of him under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhape or reſemblance, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 12, 15. we are not to think that the Godhead can be reſembled to any thing, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 27, 29. compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for unleſs we ſhould equal God to any thing, how can he be likened to it? <hi>Iſay</hi> 40. 18. 25.</p>
                  <p>Who can by ſearching find out the Almighty to perfection, <hi>Iob</hi> 11. 7, 8, 12. We are to conceive of him, as one not to be fully conceived by us, and ſo pray to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with ſuch apprehenſions of him; yet we are to believe that he is, and that he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>der of thoſe that ſeek him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. namely,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170385:71"/>
that he to whom we pray, is ſuch a God, which ſeeth and knoweth all the ſecrets of our hearts, and all our thoughts, that he is preſent with us where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are, &amp; comprehendeth us, though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend him, he is moſt holy, moſt wiſe, moſt mighty, who is ready to do for us above what we are able to ask or think, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3 18, 19, 20. This is to conceive of him in the glorious and precious dimenſions of his love, ſo ſhall we comprehend with all Saints the heighth and breadth, length and depth, and know the love of Chriſt, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth knowledge: in this ſence may we ſee him that is inviſible, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 27. For the true God is invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as appears by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Coll. 1. 15. 1 Tim. 1. 17. &amp; Tim.</hi> 6 16. The divine eſſence is not viſible to bodily eyes in this life, the eſſence ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered cannot be ſeen by the Soul in this Life, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 20. In the life to come though it be ſeen apprehenſively ſo far as the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect are capable, yet not comprehenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 1. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8, 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>How or in what order are we to direct our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to the Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity, namely, to Father, Son, and Holy Ghost?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In our Prayers we ought not to fix our ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or minds ſo upon one in the Trinity, as not thereby to be led to the other, the Father being in the Son, and the Son in the Father, and the holy Ghoſt in them both, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 10. we cannot look at one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but we muſt eye the other; they that look on Chriſt as their Mediator, muſt ſee and eye the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as giving of him ſo to be; yea and at the holy Ghoſt, as one with the Father, ſent and conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his deſignment to that office, as the Lord Chriſt himſelf ſayeth, <hi>Iſay</hi> 48. 16. and now the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170385:72"/>
Lord God and his ſpirit hath ſent me, &amp;c. we cannot look aright to the Father, but we muſt look to him through the Son, neither can we look upon the Son but by the Spirit. It is true, that in order we are firſt to direct our Prayers to God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet not as firſt or chief in honour above the other two; for even the Son, who albeit as man and as Mediator he be inferiour to the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 28. yet as God, as the Son of God, he is equal with him, <hi>Iohn 5. 18. Phill.</hi> 2. 6. and the Son is to be honored as equal with the ſame honor as the father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5 23. Albeit, as was ſaid, the holy Ghoſt be not excluded but included; ſo are we to pray unto God, through Chriſt, by the help of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 23. we are to ask the Father in the name of the Son, by the help and aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. Again, we are baptized in the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, and therefore we are to pray unto and worſhip Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and holy Ghoſt: we are to believe in the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt; and therefore we are to pray to the Father, Son and holy Ghoſt; ſo that in all external worſhip of God, one in the Trinity being named, the other are underſtood, and are not to be excluded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>Q. <hi>How can there be three, and yet but one God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> God is one in eſſence, one Jehovah, one God, and no more, and therefore God calleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>I am, Exod.</hi> 3. 14. all beſides himſelf are but created reſults of God, bits of dependances upon him; all Nations are before him as a drop of a Bucket, as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance, as a very little thing, as nothing, as leſſe than nothing, as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Iſay</hi> 40. 15 17. This one God in eſſence, ſaith <hi>Mr. Thomas Cobbert</hi> in his Treatiſe of Prayer, <hi>pag.</hi>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170385:72"/>
542 (to which I aſſent, <hi>viz.</hi>) is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal properties three, ſubſiſtences really di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, yet we are not ſo to let our thoughts feed themſelves in muſing upon the bleſſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as diſtinct in perſonal properties, but with an apprehenſion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one in eſſence, one Jehovah, one God and no more; the property of begetting is applyed to God the Father, and not to the Son, or the holy Ghoſt: he to whom the Scripture giveth the property of the only begotten Son of God, he is Jehovah, God the Son, and no other: and ſo he to whom the Scripture applyeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of proceeding, he and only he is God the holy Ghoſt, the Scripture applying to none other that property of proceeding, or being as it were breathed forth from the Father, &amp; therfore is called his Spirit, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 8. 11. &amp; from the Son; &amp; therfore is called the Sons Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 49. yet the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures never mention but one Jehovah, even when it mentions him in perſonal diſtinction three, yet eſſentially but one, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. There be three that bear record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one; the D<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine eſſence ſubſiſting in three relative properties, Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>The perſonal property of the Father is to beget, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2. 7. The perſonal property of the Son is to be begotten, <hi>John</hi> 1. 14, 18. The perſonal property of the holy Ghoſt is to proceed from the Father and the Son, <hi>John</hi> 14. 26. &amp; 15. 26.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall Iſay more? As God for the helping of us to underſtand his eſſence, is pleaſed to take unto himſelf certain names and attributes, by the help of which we may the better underſtand his eſſence, ſo alſo is he pleaſed to take unto himſelf
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170385:73"/>
certain names &amp; appellations to help us to the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding of his ſubſiſtance, &amp;c. yet there is but only (<hi>one</hi>) living &amp; true God, who is infinite in being &amp; perfection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a moſt pure Spirit, inviſibly without body, parts or paſſions, immutable, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, incomprehenſible, working all things accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the counſel of his own will, he is the alone Fountain of all beings, of whom, through whom, and to whom are all things, in his ſight all things are made manifeſt, his knowledge is infinite, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and independent, he is moſt holy in all his Counſels, in all his Works, in all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, &amp;c. But if any demand farther, How can there be three, and yet but one God? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, great is the myſtery, the Son in the Father, and the Father in the Son, and the Spirit of truth, which is by the Father and the Son, <hi>John</hi> 14. 11. <hi>John</hi> 15. 26. &amp; 14. 26.</p>
                  <p>So that in this myſtery a Chriſtian is to believe, what reaſon cannot comprehend; the Father ſent forth his Son, the Son ſent forth the holy Ghoſt, yet Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, was never ſeparated one from another; Take a candle burning and there is ſubſtance, light and heat, and yet not three candles, but one candle; Look upon the good man of a Houſe, and you ſhall find that he is a Husband to his Wife, a Father to his Children, a Maſter to his Servants, and yet not three men, but one man; ſo in the unity of the God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> head, there be three of one ſubſtance, power, and eternity, God the Father, God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt; the Father is of none, neither begotten nor proceeding, the Son is eternally begotten of the Father, the holy Ghoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally proceeding from the Father and the Son, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
